<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The saints aduantage or The welfare of the faithfull, in the worst times A sermon, preached at the Hage the 18. of May, 1623. before the most high, and mighty princesse, Elizabeth, by the grace of God, Queene of Bohemia, Countesse Palatine of the Rhene, &amp;c. By Iohn Wing, an vnworthy minister of the gospel and pastor to the English Church at Flishing in Zealand.</title>
            <author>Wing, John, of Flushing, Zealand.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1623</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 180 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 47 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A15580</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 25847</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S120119</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99855319</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99855319</idno>
            <idno type="VID">20806</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A15580)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 20806)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1563:17)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The saints aduantage or The welfare of the faithfull, in the worst times A sermon, preached at the Hage the 18. of May, 1623. before the most high, and mighty princesse, Elizabeth, by the grace of God, Queene of Bohemia, Countesse Palatine of the Rhene, &amp;c. By Iohn Wing, an vnworthy minister of the gospel and pastor to the English Church at Flishing in Zealand.</title>
                  <author>Wing, John, of Flushing, Zealand.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 84 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Martin Abraham vander Nolck, dwelling at the signe of the Printing-house,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At Flishing :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1623.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:20806:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE SAINTS ADVANTAGE OR The welfare of the FAITHFVLL, in the worſt times. <hi>A Sermon,</hi> Preached at the Hage the 18. of May, 1623. before the moſt High, and Mighty Princeſſe, <hi>ELIZABETH,</hi> by the Grace of <hi>GOD, QVEENE</hi> of Bohemia, Counteſſe Palatine of the Rhene, &amp;c. By <hi>IOHN WING,</hi> an vnworthy Miniſter of the goſpel and Paſtor to the English Church at <hi>FLISHING</hi> in <hi>ZEALAND.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>2 Cor. 1.3.4.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p n="3"> 3. Bleſſed be God the Father of our Lord Ieſus Christ, the Fathers, mercies, and God of all conſolation.</p>
               <p n="4"> 4. Who comforteth vs in all our tribulation, that we may be able to comfort them which are in any trouble, by the comfort where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with we our ſelues are comforted of God.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>AT FLISHING,</hi> Printed by <hi>Martin Abraham vander Nolck,</hi> dwelling at the ſigne of the Printing-houſe, 1623.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:20806:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:20806:2"/>
            <head>TO THE Moſt, High, and Mighty Princeſſe, <hi>ELIZABETH,</hi> by the grace of God, <hi>QVEENE</hi> of Bohemia, Counteſſe Palatine of the Rhene, &amp;c.</head>
            <head type="sub"> 
               <hi>IOHN WING,</hi> Paſtor of the <hi>English</hi> Church at <hi>Flushing,</hi> in <hi>Zealand,</hi> wisheth all encreaſe of grace, and peace, &amp; whatſoever may enlarge all preſent hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pines <hi>on earth,</hi> and aſſure that which is eternall, <hi>in heaven.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>MOST GRACIOVS PRINCESSE,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>naſmuch <hi>as it pleaſed your moſt</hi> excellent <hi>Majeſty,</hi> to vouchſafe a <hi>Gracious eare</hi> to the weake vtterance of theſe medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, I am comfortablely encouraged to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent a more compleate diſcovery of them, to your <hi>Princely eyes,</hi> not that I account them worthy (as they are myne) of the <hi>leaſt looke of Majeſty;</hi> but truſting <hi>who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> to that clemency &amp; favour, which I humbly entreate, may thyne from you, vpon this my poore endeavour; it having (next to the honour of the moſt high God) her only reſpect, and ayme, at your Majesties preſent, and furture condition; a true <hi>type</hi> wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, is here tendered by him, whoſe ſoule doth daily ſue vnto the <hi>King of Kings,</hi> that as he hath meaſured vnto, (and you haue shared with,) <hi>Moſes,</hi> and <hi>David,</hi> many tribulations in the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance of their honour, and renowne, and after made them ſo much the more <hi>famous, admired,</hi> &amp; <hi>victorious:</hi> So it, might pleaſe the ſame Lord to alott you the ſweete happines of <hi>their</hi> iſſue, which was most bleſſed and glorious; to alay the distaſte of that bitter beginning, which (vnto nature) ſeemeth ſomewhat tarte, and greivous; and together with that peereleſſe greatnes
<pb facs="tcp:20806:3"/> which they enjoyed on earth, the ſame glory and joy, which they poſeſſe in heaven. The <hi>Great God</hi> of heaven and earth bleſſe, with the richest <hi>abundance,</hi> &amp; <hi>combination</hi> of his <hi>rareſt,</hi> and <hi>beſt</hi> blesſings, your <hi>Royall Head, &amp; Huſband;</hi> your <hi>Highnes,</hi> all your hopefull <hi>Plants,</hi> &amp; <hi>Princely poſterity,</hi> that your <hi>Crowne</hi> may yet flourish, your enemyes may ever pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rish, and you all, may be made <hi>mirrours</hi> of <hi>Majeſty,</hi> and <hi>Royalty,</hi> to all generations.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your</hi> Majeſties <hi>in all duty to be commanded.</hi> IOHN WING.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:20806:3"/>
            <head>To my worthy, and Right welbeloved Freinds, <hi>Maiſter Caleb Cockcroft,</hi> Treaſurer <hi>to the famous followship of</hi> Merchant Adventurers <hi>of England, reſident at</hi> Delft And vnto <hi>Maiſter Iohn Barkelay. Maiſter Arthur Tyndall. Maiſter Iohn Quarlys. Maiſter William Clarke.</hi> Bretheren <hi>of the ſame Society Iohn Wing,</hi> wisheth all preſent welfare, and proſperity o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> earth, which may further their future felicity in heaven.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Owſoever I haue hereto-fore ſaluted your whole ſociety, in that vnfayned af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection which I beare vnto you all; yet, <hi>n</hi> being in ſome particuler engagements more bound to ſome in ſpeciall, then to all in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall; I preſume vpon your kinde acceptance of this poore manifeſtation of my loue to you, having had large experience of yours, to me. A ſmall token is welcome from a true freind; and I nothing doubt but this shalbe the better entertayned, not only be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is ſent from ſuch a one, but alſo, for that it contayneth matter of Advantage, and that (as I truſt I may boldely ſay) to your ſelues, as vnto thoſe, who deſyring, and endeavouring to be of that number to whome theſe moſt worthy preiveledges doe ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertayne, shall (in your due ſeeking) be right ſure to enjoy, thoſe many &amp; moſt bleſſed benefitts, which are here by vs diſcovered, and by God himſelf en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayled, to all his faithfull ones, for ever. And inaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as it is noe good <hi>decorum</hi> to make a long E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtle, to a litle booke, I am more breife with you then (otherwiſe) my loue would let me be, which
<pb facs="tcp:20806:4"/> could much more enlarge it ſelf, if it were meete <hi>(at preſent)</hi> ſoe to doe. But, what is not convenient now to ſay to your ſelues, I shall not ceaſe to vtter in my poore requeſts for you vnto <hi>him,</hi> who is <hi>Lord</hi> over all, and rich vnto all: To whoſe grace, &amp; loue, I leaue you, and all that are yours, beſeeching him to enrich you with all the graces of his good ſpirit, that may giue you a bleſſed, and abundant entrance into his glorious Kingdome, by Ieſus Chriſt, both your Lord, and ours; in whome I reſt</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yours vnfaynedly, for any good to my vtmoſt ability. IOHN WING.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>From my houſe in Flushing, <date>March 7. 1623.</date>
                  </hi>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:20806:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>To the Christian Reader</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Eloved in the Lord, ſeing promiſe is debt, and performance alone the only diſcharge that can giue plenary ſatiſfaction; I muſt <hi>(at preſent)</hi> deale as poore debtors oft-times are enfor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ced, to <hi>pray</hi> where they cannot <hi>pay,</hi> and to entreat yet longer time, for that which was due <hi>long a-goe.</hi> It is neere foure yeares, ſince I began to engage my ſelf vnto thee, for the perfecting of my <hi>matrimoniall treatiſe</hi> then (in part) published. To this day, I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe I haue not finished the ſame, for I mett with ſuch cumbrance, hynderance, and inconvenience, in that <hi>litle,</hi> which was but as a <hi>praeface</hi> to the reſt, that I durſt not adventure to ſet vpon the remaynder, being the farre greater part. Yet, I am not out of all hope, ere long to doe it; and in the meane time. I thought good to ſend <hi>this Sermon</hi> abroad, wherein I haue endeavoured the cure, of one of the moſt <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon ſores,</hi> that hath come to my obſervation in theſe evill times; to wit, the hard conceit, that not only the <hi>vngodly</hi> doe harbour of Gods people, but <hi>they</hi> of themſelues, eſpecially if outward things goe hard with them &amp; the times doe not favour, but diſtaſte, and frowne vpon them. <hi>Beholde</hi> here, a man that was taught of God, to know ſo much of the very meaneſt eſtate of the members of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> that he willingly left to be <hi>mighty</hi> in the worlde, to make one among them in their <hi>meaneſſe,</hi> &amp; miſery; and by his practiſe made it manifeſt, that his perſwaſion was quite contrary to the baſe opinion of men, touching the ſaints of <hi>God.</hi> And if he were led vnto this excellent eſtimation by
<pb facs="tcp:20806:5" rendition="simple:additions"/> 
               <hi>extraordinary inſpiration</hi> from God, is it not <hi>extraordinary impiety,</hi> to thinke or ſpeake otherwiſe of them? Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rely, ſoe farre as <hi>God</hi> did informe the one, <hi>Satan</hi> doth infatuate the other. Reade and ponder the particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers, <hi>(but first correct theſe few errors of the Printer)</hi> and pray to <hi>that God</hi> for me, to whome I am, and shalbe a ſuitor for thee, for thy preſent, and future welfare.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>
                  <hi>Farewell in the Lord; in whome I am thyne.</hi> 
               </salute>
               <signed>IOHN WING</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell role="label"> 
                        <hi>Pag.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell role="label"> 
                        <hi>Lin.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell role="label"> 
                        <hi>Error.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell role="label"> 
                        <hi>Correction.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1.</cell>
                     <cell>4.</cell>
                     <cell>as it is,</cell>
                     <cell>it is</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>3.</cell>
                     <cell>1.</cell>
                     <cell>of penman,</cell>
                     <cell>of the penman,</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>29.</cell>
                     <cell>at muſt,</cell>
                     <cell>it muſt,</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>4.</cell>
                     <cell>4.</cell>
                     <cell>wth theſe,</cell>
                     <cell>with theſe,</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>6.</cell>
                     <cell>33.</cell>
                     <cell>he ſecond,</cell>
                     <cell>the ſecond,</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>13,</cell>
                     <cell>23.</cell>
                     <cell>&amp; deights.</cell>
                     <cell>&amp; delights,</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>17.</cell>
                     <cell>3.</cell>
                     <cell>yeed him,</cell>
                     <cell>yeelde him,</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>18.</cell>
                     <cell>5.</cell>
                     <cell>of he,</cell>
                     <cell>if he</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>28.</cell>
                     <cell>in this,</cell>
                     <cell>in his,</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>21.</cell>
                     <cell>4.</cell>
                     <cell>wath the,</cell>
                     <cell>with the,</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>30.</cell>
                     <cell>32.</cell>
                     <cell>happing to,</cell>
                     <cell>hoping to,</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>34.</cell>
                     <cell>24.</cell>
                     <cell>able giue,</cell>
                     <cell>able to giue,</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>37.</cell>
                     <cell>28.</cell>
                     <cell>byrd it,</cell>
                     <cell>byrd that,</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>41.</cell>
                     <cell>34.</cell>
                     <cell>ſull of,</cell>
                     <cell>ſull of,</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>65.</cell>
                     <cell>29.</cell>
                     <cell>muſt shall,</cell>
                     <cell>muſt be shall,</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>66.</cell>
                     <cell>1.</cell>
                     <cell>all this,</cell>
                     <cell>all his,</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>68.</cell>
                     <cell>5.</cell>
                     <cell>to greſſe,</cell>
                     <cell>to gueſſe,</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>10.</cell>
                     <cell>pemiſſes,</cell>
                     <cell>premiſſes,</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>69.</cell>
                     <cell>7.</cell>
                     <cell>pilaished with,</cell>
                     <cell>perished with,</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>72.</cell>
                     <cell>1.</cell>
                     <cell>everabundantly,</cell>
                     <cell>over-abundantly</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>10.</cell>
                     <cell>the pemiſſes,</cell>
                     <cell>the premiſſes,</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>77.</cell>
                     <cell>10.</cell>
                     <cell>if the,</cell>
                     <cell>if they,</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>14.</cell>
                     <cell>gnaw owne,</cell>
                     <cell>gnaw out.</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:20806:5"/>
            <head>THE SAINTS ADVANTAGE Or The welfare of the Faithfull, in the worſt times. In a Sermon On </head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Heb. 11.26.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>— Esteeming the reproach of Christ greater riches then the treaſures in Egypt.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is not much materiall vnto vs, neither will it be worth our time and labour, to looke after the <hi>Writer</hi> of this <hi>Epistle,</hi> ſeing as it is paſt queſtion that the <hi>H. Ghost</hi> was the <hi>Author</hi> of the ſame. And therefore we will not trouble our ſelues or you, with any needeles and fruitles ſearch, what man of <hi>God</hi> it might be that pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned it, ſeing we are throughly perſwaded that God himſelf inſpired it; who having great abundance and variety of divine <hi>Secretayes,</hi> might employ whome he pleaſed in this ſervice, and yet not be pleaſed to tell vs who it was, whome he did employ in the ſame. It is not the leſſe <hi>Canonicall,</hi> or <hi>Authentike,</hi> becauſe we
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:20806:6"/> cannot tell who wrote it: the matter of it is knowne to be <hi>Gods,</hi> though no <hi>name</hi> of any man of God, be praefixed there vnto. The which, ſince the Lord in great wiſdome hath concealed, how can we without groſſe folly endeavour to diſcover it? he having thought <hi>good</hi> to hyde it, it muſt be thought <hi>evill</hi> in vs to make enquirie after it.</p>
            <p>What; cannot a good meſſage of glad tydings be welcome from our beſt freind, vnleſſe we may know the meſſengers name that brought it; Or shall not a <hi>Patent</hi> (from the <hi>King</hi>) contayning matter of <hi>profit,</hi> or <hi>preferment;</hi> or a <hi>Pardon</hi> of ſome foule fact, be accepted and beleeved, if withall we may not be certifyed (by name) which of the <hi>Secretaries of State</hi> did write it? would not all the world cenſure it for vnreaſonable abſurdity, abſurd incivility, yea, and for moſt vncivill, and inſufferable inſolency, if a man should ſtand vpon theſe tearmes with his <hi>betters,</hi> and thus refuſe the meanes of his welfare? were not ſuch a one well <hi>worthy</hi> to be woful, for want of that which he ſo <hi>vnworthily</hi> refuſed? And if thus it be, in theſe temporall occurrents, which can concerne but our preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t externall advantage, it muſt of neceſſity be ſo much the more evill, and intollerable, in theſe ſpirit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uall affayres, by how much in them, we haue to doe with him, whoſe excellency and glory doth ſurmount all mens; and in thoſe paſſages, which both in their owne nature, and in their conſequence to vs, doe infinitely and incomparablely exceede, all the bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitts of this preſent life, as being concerning the eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall, and inconceivable happines of our whole man for ever and ever in the heavens.</p>
            <p>Had any jmportant point of holy niformation de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pended
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:20806:6" rendition="simple:additions"/> vpon the notice of <hi>Pen-man</hi> of this part of ſcripture, we should aſſuredly have knowne who he had beene, for we have great reaſon to beleeue that our good God would not haue witholden any good thing from vs, we may therefore well co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>clude that no thing could be gotten by it, ſeing the <hi>most wiſe God</hi> will not let vs know it; and what idle and ſenſeleſſe <hi>buſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bodyes</hi> are we then, to make our ſelues ſuch worthles and vnproffitable worke, as will not pay for the time which is ſpent about it, nor yeeld any advantage, if it were finished, and the <hi>Writer</hi> revealed.</p>
            <p>The more are men to be balmed, (<hi>Divines</hi> eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, &amp; the <hi>beſt</hi> moſt of all), who make ſoe much a-doe about this particuler, as if the <hi>authority,</hi> or <hi>nullity</hi> of this <hi>Epistle</hi> lay vpon the <hi>Writer,</hi> rather then vpon the <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thour</hi> of the ſame It would weary and tyre any man, and make him to mourne in his very ſoule, to ſee how men of eminent excellency, &amp; worthy parts, have toyled in this <hi>tituler,</hi> (I had almoſt ſayd, <hi>triviall</hi>) buſi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes, diſputed betweene <hi>Papist</hi> and <hi>Papist,</hi> betweene <hi>Proteſtant</hi> and <hi>Papist,</hi> yea, betweene <hi>Protestant</hi> and <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testant,</hi> as if it were a matter of more then words or names (as <hi>Gallio</hi> ſayd) and of ſome mighty conſequen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce, whenas indeed it is not, neither hath any inferen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce of any force or fruit anexed vnto it, whoſe name ſoever it beare.</p>
            <p>Some will haue it to be PAVLS, and for prooffe they plead: 1 The ſtile, and ſtrayne of it to be ſoe like <hi>his</hi> every where, that it muſt needes be <hi>his owne</hi> here: 2 The cloſe, or concluſion of this Epiſtle cap. 13.25. being the ſame which <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith he ſaluted his freinds, and shutt vp all his <hi>Epistles</hi> withall: 3 The authority of the Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> writing (as is thought) to the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brewes
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:20806:7" rendition="simple:additions"/> ſaying, 2 Pet. 3.15.16. that <hi>Paul</hi> had written to them, &amp; ſeemeth to point at this Epiſtle, becauſe of the obſcurity &amp; difficulty of divers things therein: &amp; together with theſe, divers other obſervable things are inſtanced, and vrged in the body of the Epiſtle, (too long for vs now to relate) which make much probability that <hi>Paul</hi> wrote it.</p>
            <p>Some others againe will not haue it to be <hi>Pauls,</hi> but are perſwaded ſome other holy man of God had the penning of it, and they plead: 1 That his name is not to it, whereas <hi>Pauls</hi> manner was to ſet his name to all that are vndoubtedly his: 2 That, he who wro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te this <hi>Epiſtle</hi> ſeemeth not to haue had the matter thereof <hi>jmmediately</hi> from God (which <hi>Paul</hi> evermo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re had) but <hi>mediately</hi> from ſome other, who heard it from <hi>Chriſt,</hi> as the words cap. 2.1.2.3. doe jmport: to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with ſome other likely paſſages which doe jmprooue <hi>Pauls</hi> penning of it.</p>
            <p>And this <hi>vnneceſſary controverſy</hi> hath coſt much time, &amp; paines, even among men of <hi>great</hi> learning &amp; godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, who yet I am perſwaded, cannot but know, that neither the <hi>Inſcriptions,</hi> nor <hi>Subſcriptions</hi> of theſe <hi>Epiſtles</hi> which haue beene written by ſeverall <hi>Apostles,</hi> are, or can in any good reaſon be accounted <hi>Scripture,</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering how many juſt exceptions may be alledged againſt ſundry of both ſorts, to make them miſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted, and ſubject to vndeniable ambiguity, whereas all <hi>Scripture</hi> is abſolutely infallible. How is it then that men lay out their money for that which is not bread?
<note place="margin"> Iſa. 55.2.</note> and take ſuch paines for things that cannot proffit? Summe vp all the <hi>Items</hi> vrged of either ſide, what will the <hi>Totall</hi> amount vnto, but this, that inaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as ſome probability lyeth on either part, the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:20806:7"/> is aſſurance on neither. Againe, admit &amp; ſuppoſe it were ſure on one ſide, either the <hi>affirmative,</hi> that it were <hi>Pauls,</hi> what are we the better, or the wiſer in the way to heaven for the certanity hereof? or on the <hi>negatiue</hi> that it was none of <hi>Pauls,</hi> but that <hi>Luke</hi> (as ſome thinke) or <hi>Barnabas,</hi> or <hi>Clement</hi> (as others conceiue) did pen it, what holynes or happines is woonne, when all this is done? ſurely none. The <hi>most</hi> that can come of the former is only this, that we may call it <hi>[the Epistle of Paul to the Hebrewes]</hi> and put his na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me into our coppies, as it is in all others except one (as one obſerveth). The <hi>least</hi> that can come of the latter, is, that we leaue out <hi>Pauls</hi> name, and all names, and call it as we finde it, <hi>[the Epiſtle to the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brewes]</hi> which title or inſcription, being indifferent to either ſide, we will reſt in the ſame as it is, without further contention or inquiſition, ſeing either <hi>Pauls,</hi> or any other name noted before, may be <hi>probabely put in,</hi> and yet <hi>ſafely left out,</hi> let vs take it without any at all, and ſo proceed from the <hi>writer,</hi> to the <hi>matter</hi> contay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in that which is written, eſpecially in that litle parcell which hath beene read, and in the revealing wherof, we intend (by <hi>Gods</hi> grace) to inſiſt at this time.</p>
            <p>And that we may the better come to comprehend what the will and mynd of the Lord is therein, it shalbe good to goe back a litle, to looke vpon the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall ſtate of the whole chapter, and to take ſuch a view of the ſame, as may further vs in the particuler of theſe words.</p>
            <p>And what is this chapter (being well conſidered) but a kinde of <hi>ſummary</hi> or <hi>abridgment,</hi> of the olde Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament in that part therof eſpecially, which is <hi>histo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricall,</hi>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:20806:8"/> and contayneth the diſcovery of things done in matter of fact, by thoſe moſt famous <hi>worthyes</hi> of the Lord, the eminency of whoſe faith, and excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of the fruits of the ſame, haue here a moſt glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons remembrance, being left vpon an everlaſting re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord that cannot faile, but muſt and shall remayne to the <hi>bleſſed memoriall of thoſe juſt men,</hi> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Prov. </seg>
               </label> the tryall of whoſe faith having beene more precious then gold,
<note place="margin"> 1 Pet. 1.7</note> shalbe found vnto (the Lords, and their owne) praiſe, and honour, and glory, at the appearance of Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Of which <hi>worthyes</hi> (both men and women) we haue here a particuler <hi>catalogue,</hi> many of them being <hi>(by name)</hi> perſonally expreſſed, from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of the chapter to the <hi>33. verſe:</hi> and others apparantly included (though <hi>not named)</hi> from thence to the end. And in this <hi>catalogue</hi> it pleaſeth the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt to keepe an excellent <hi>decorum,</hi> in an or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly and methodicall diſtribution of the perſons, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the times wherein they lived, and the <hi>Chronologie</hi> of the world, in the moſt famous <hi>Periods</hi> of the ſame vnder the olde Teſtament.</p>
            <p>It beginneth with righteous <hi>Abell</hi> ver. 4. who lived not long after the creation (being the ſecond from <hi>Adam</hi>) and goeth on from him to <hi>Enoch</hi> the ſeaventh from <hi>Adam</hi> (as <hi>Iude</hi> call's him:)
<note place="margin"> ver. 14.</note> and from <hi>Enoch</hi> to <hi>Noah,</hi> and ſoe finisheth the firſt famous period of the world, from the <hi>Creation,</hi> to the <hi>Flood;</hi> and begin's the ſecond from the flood to <hi>Abraham,</hi> and the reſt of thoſe peereleſſe <hi>Patriarchs,</hi> who lived after the <hi>Flood,</hi> and before the <hi>Law</hi> till <hi>Moſes;</hi> who overliving them all, did finish the ſecond famous period from the <hi>Flood</hi> to the giving of the <hi>Law,</hi> and made entrance in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:20806:8" rendition="simple:additions"/> the third, from <hi>Moſes</hi> &amp; the <hi>Law</hi> given, to the time of the <hi>Iudges:</hi> and ſoe from thence-forward to the change of the civill government of the <hi>Iewes,</hi> from <hi>Iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges</hi> to <hi>Kings:</hi> and vnder their <hi>Kings,</hi> both during the time of their ſetled and peaceable ſtate, and alſo thence, vnto thoſe interrupted and miſerable dayes where-in captivity prevayled; both at the <hi>first, in part</hi> to their diſturbance once, and againe for a time; and <hi>at the last</hi> to the <hi>totall</hi> and finall, downefall and over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw of that nation, as touching any viſible face either of a <hi>civill,</hi> or an <hi>eccleſiasticall</hi> eſtate.</p>
            <p>Now in this <hi>Campe Royall,</hi> of ſuch as are here num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred, named, and made glorious by the notable fruits of their faith; ſome haue renowned themſelues (as ſervants) <hi>actively</hi> by doing, others haue beene ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prooved (as ſouldiers) <hi>paſſively</hi> by ſuffering; but <hi>Moſes</hi> (being the <hi>man</hi> meant in our <hi>text</hi>) is truly intereſſed into either condition, and hath made <hi>double</hi> declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his faith, in both kindes of thoſe things that are reported of him, for we finde both what he <hi>did,</hi> and what he <hi>endured,</hi> and ſoe much of either, as doth manifeſt him for one of the rareſt mirrours among thoſe many, who are muſtered and magnified here, to haue <hi>ſought the good fight of faith;</hi> and that, in all thoſe occurrents that came to paſſe (on his part) either before <hi>Iſraell</hi> went out of <hi>Egypt,</hi> or after; for within one of theſe two computations of time, all is comprehended which is recorded of him, and for which he is here applauded by the holy Ghoſt.</p>
            <p>The powerfull worke of faith appearing in him before the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> departure from vnder <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> had a <hi>twofolde</hi> operation.</p>
            <p n="1"> 1. While he was yet a <hi>Courtier,</hi> (and great in Court
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:20806:9"/> too) being for ſoe long time the adopted, and repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted ſon of <hi>Pharaohs</hi> daughter, in which time faith wrought in his hart a <hi>gracious reſolution,</hi> to giue over that <hi>glorious condition.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2"> 2. When he put this reſolution into practiſe, ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting of the <hi>Court,</hi> and forſaking <hi>Egypt</hi> for a ſeaſon, and afterwards returning by warrant from God, (and as the Lords Ambaſſadour) to worke out the peoples freedome: and theſe paſſages are parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culated vnto vs, in the 24.25.26. and 27. verſes.</p>
            <p>The further efficacy wherein his faith shyned, after he had left <hi>Egypt</hi> altogether, &amp; was gone thence with Gods people, is evident in ſuch relation as is made therof, ver. 28.29.</p>
            <p>Our text is a part of the former power of his faith, while he was yet in <hi>Egypt,</hi> wherein, (and that while he was yet a great <hi>Peere,</hi> among theſe <hi>Pagans</hi>) the Lord mightily, and <hi>extraordinarily,</hi> wrought in him jmme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately by himſelf, without all ordinary meanes (that man can jmagine) this <hi>great</hi> grace of <hi>Faith,</hi> which by a holy kinde of heavenly and divine <hi>violence,</hi> enforced him to theſe 3. things which lye in theſe 3. verſes.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> 1. To relinquish and renounce his whole eſtate, with all the honours, and advantages annexed there vnto, all which, although he had long enjo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yed them, and they were many and great, at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, and might (poſſibly) haue beene much grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter afterward, through the hope of his further ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing by meanes of the favour of <hi>Pharachs daughter,</hi> yet faith make's no thing of theſe mighty things, but he freely forſaketh all, and willingly refuſeth to be called or accounted <hi>her Son,</hi> ver. 24.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 2. To chuſe (in ſtead of this rejected honour and
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:20806:9"/> royalty) the miſerable and moſt afflicted ſtate of the people of God, who were in the greateſt ſlave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and vnder the moſt grevious tyranny that could be, ver. 25.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> 3. To judge and cenſure (and that with a righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous judgment) both his former practiſes of <hi>refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing</hi> and <hi>chuſing,</hi> to be lawfull, and good, and well pleaſing to the Lord, ver. 26.</p>
            <p>And this <hi>third</hi> is the only thing, where with we haue to doe, yet before we enter vpon it in <hi>particuler,</hi>
               <note place="margin"> Faith wrought extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarily.</note> we haue one obſervable thing to note in the <hi>generall,</hi> to wit; That thoſe graces which are jmmediately, and extraordinarily wrought in man by the Lord, doe carry mans hart extraordinarily towards the Lord. If God worke faith extraordinarily in <hi>Abraham</hi> he will leaue his conutrey; he will ſacrifice his ſon, <hi>doe</hi> any thing, <hi>deny</hi> nothing, at Gods command. If in <hi>Moſes</hi> he will leaue all the honour, and riches, and happines in the world, and expoſe himſelf to any mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery, danger, and infamy for the honour of God. The ſame might be ſayd of <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> of <hi>Eſther,</hi> and many other, whoſe graces haue yeelded rare &amp; wonderfull <hi>fruit,</hi> becauſe they ſprung from more then an ordinary <hi>roote.</hi> The more jmmediate any mans graces are from God, the more admirable are the manifeſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of thoſe graces before God.</p>
            <p>But we intend not to ſtay here:
<note place="margin"> The parts of the text.</note> let vs therefore ſet forward to this <hi>third</hi> effect of <hi>Moſes</hi> faith in the words of the 26. ver: (contayning the eſtimation of his ſayd acts) and in them, we haue to conſider 3. things.</p>
            <p n="1"> 1. The guide and ground of this his eſtimation, to wit, FAITH; not common ſenſe, nor carnall rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:20806:10"/> for neither of theſe would haue endured any ſuch proceedings.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 2. The things eſteemed, to wit, the <hi>reproach of Chriſt,</hi> and the <hi>riches of Egypt,</hi> and theſe being ballan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced by <hi>faith,</hi> and layd one, againſt the other, the former is found to be much better, and farre be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the latter.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> 3. The reaſon of this his opinion, which ariſeth not from any reſpect of things <hi>preſent</hi> and <hi>ſenſible,</hi> but only and wholy from the happy apprehenſion, and aſſurance that he had of that <hi>inviſible,</hi> and <hi>infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite</hi> recompence of reward layd vp for thoſe who can forgoe all things for Gods glory.</p>
            <p>And theſe are the parts of this verſe; touching which, we shall not neede to make any ſtay vpon the interpretation of any of them, there being noe ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcurity, or ambiguity, but all being eaſy and open to the meaneſt capacity: we will therefore haſten to the matter of inſtruction which they doe adminiſter vnto vs.</p>
            <p>And here,
<note place="margin"> A ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perty of Faith.</note> in the very firſt word <hi>[Esteeming]</hi> (inaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as his faith made him thus to <hi>eſteeme</hi>) we might note vnto you, one excellent property, and power of true faith, which is, to alter the mynde, opinion, and judgment of man from that it was, touching the world, and all things therein; to eſteeme the beſt things therein ſoe baſe as to preferre, and chuſe the baſeſt eſtate in the world, before that which in the eye of the world is the beſt.</p>
            <p>Time was, that <hi>Moſes</hi> could make vſe of, and po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſe the honours of <hi>Egypt,</hi> for forty yeares together, but now (vnto faith) affliction is better then promo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, ſlavery then honour; he will rather be a captive
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:20806:10"/> with Gods people, then a gallant <hi>courtier,</hi> even the ſon of a Kings daughter: he is now otherwiſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceited, opinionated, and perſwaded then before he was; <hi>Faith</hi> hath ſoe altered the caſe with him, that he is nothing ſo mynded as he was.</p>
            <p>It is no marvell that the holy Ghoſt oppoſeth <hi>faith,</hi> and <hi>ſence,</hi> and that the Apoſtle ſaith, [<hi>we walke</hi> by faith,
<note place="margin"> Cor.</note> 
               <hi>and not by ſight]</hi> for they looked not on things that were ſeene, but lived by faith, which fed it ſelf, and faſtened them, on things not ſeens, and ſoe they ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted and judged all things baſe and vile,
<note place="margin"> Phil. 3.8.</note> yea <hi>loſſe</hi> and <hi>dung,</hi> (yea as moſt loathſome and excecrable ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crements, as the word ſignifyes:) and could well brooke to haue themſelues accounted the baſe of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcouring of all things, through the excellency of faith that was in them.</p>
            <p>Let no man vainely boaſt of this vertue, or jma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine he hath himſelf poſeſt of this ſinguler grace, to whoſe mynde, judgment, and eſtimation, all things are not ſoe baſe and abhominable, that he can (being put to it by God) moſt willingly abandon, and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horre all riches and glory; and freely take vp all af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction, wretchednes and miſery; yea, and rather (as our <hi>Moſes</hi> here) make a good choyſe of the <hi>worſt,</hi> then make an ill vſe of the <hi>beſt,</hi> that the world can afford. True <hi>faith</hi> (where it is) is of a noble, heroicall, hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly, and divine diſpoſition, and carryes the hart of man into <hi>high contempt</hi> of the things which before he had in <hi>higheſt eſteeme,</hi> ſcorning in the leaſt, to ſtoope to the greateſt and moſt glorious lure, that can be offred of the things that are below, &amp; doth diſdayne to looke after thoſe advantages which are moſt deare vnto others.</p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:20806:11"/>
            <p>But we muſt not dwell here neither, neither is it our preſent purpoſe to proſecute this point, but to ſet forward vnto that whereon we intend <hi>(by Gods grace)</hi> to inſiſt: and that is taken from the <hi>ſecond</hi> conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration; which is of the things eſteemed, and they (being compared one with another) the <hi>[reproach of Chriſt]</hi> is found farre to exceede, and to be much bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, then the <hi>treaſures in Egypt.]</hi> From wence the mayne thing which we haue to learne for our in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction is thus much.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doctrine </seg>
               </label> 
               <hi>That the</hi> worſt eſtate <hi>of a childe of God, is better, then the</hi> beſt eſtate <hi>of any wicked man.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Note it well; we ſay and avouch, that the worſt e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate of Gods childe, is better then the beſt of a wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked man.</p>
            <p>For the better vnderſtanding and beleeving of which point, becauſe at <hi>firſt ſight,</hi> it may ſeeme a ſtrang <hi>Paradexe,</hi> and a propoſition jmpoſſible to be true; it shalbe neceſſary before we come to proue the ſame, to explane it before you, and to giue all men to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand, what we meane by the <hi>worſt eſtate</hi> of Gods childe, and by the <hi>best estate</hi> of a wicked man.</p>
            <p>And (in a word) <hi>thus</hi> we meane: that, looke what the world (that is, the men of the worlde) doe eſteeme and judge (on the one part) to be the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt and moſt miſerable ſtate of any good man: and alſo what they themſelues doe againe conceive (on the other part) to be their owne moſt happy and comfortable condition, that (on either part) we in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend in this our inſtruction.</p>
            <p>Now all men doe know, that the world doth re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute, affliction, diſgrace, tyranny, perſecution, and all kinde of cruelty, and ſlavery, to be the vnhap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pieſt
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:20806:11" rendition="simple:additions"/> caſe a man can poſſibly be in: and on the other ſide, the honour, wealth, proſperity, and abundance of all things which the hart of man can wish, when e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very thing goes with him as he would haue it, and all things ſettle vpon him to his ſoules content: this is adjudged the happieſt ſtate of him, or them that haue it. And this is that we account the beſt of the one; and the worſt of the other, even that, which themſelues doe account ſoe, we aſke no other interpreters of our meaning, then the men of the earth, in their or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary and vniverſall opinion.</p>
            <p>And of theſe eſtates being thus vnderſtood, we are to proue, and make good, that the former <hi>(being the worſt)</hi> is better to a childe of God, then the latter <hi>(being the beſt)</hi> can be, to any vngodly man: yea, that the very gall and wormewood, and the moſt <hi>bitter</hi> and envenomed things which the world can giue the goldly to drinke; are happier, and more holſome to digeſt, then the <hi>ſweetest</hi> portion of their cup, who are vngodly, when it is filled vp to the brym, and run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning over with all the rareſt, and moſt pleaſant com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions which the world can powre into it, of all manner of delicacies and deights that are to be deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, either for pleaſure, or for proffit, or for honour, or for eaſe, or for ought elſe, which may take vp and bewitch the mynde of a worldly man. And thus our meaning being explayned, the matter remayneth now to be proved.</p>
            <p>The full confirmation wherof, will ſoone ariſe out of the due conſideration of our text, and the true contents of the ſame, in caſe we take ſuch true no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of them is we ought.</p>
            <p>Were there no other man but <hi>Moſes,</hi> no other evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:20806:12"/> or example to make good the point but <hi>hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone,</hi> in that which he hath here done; he only were able to avouch the truth we teach againſt all <hi>gayneſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yers</hi> whatſoever; inaſmuch as we finde his practiſe to be of worthy approbation with God, and alſo wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy to be a moſt worthy preſident vnto vs from God, and that it is recorded, not only for <hi>his commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation,</hi> but for <hi>our mitation</hi> alſo: in which act of his let vs note theſe particuler and ſinguler paſſages, which may leade vs the more to beleeue the truth we are to confirme.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> 
               <hi>First,</hi> how he was brought into the favour of <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raoh,</hi> to wit, by a ſtrange and extraordinary provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of God, diſpoſing his parents there to hyde him, where the daughter of <hi>Pharaoh</hi> muſt diſcover him, and in diſpoſing her hart (having found him) to commiſerate the miſerable and helples condition of this forlorne and deſolate infant, whome his owne fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and mother durſt not owne, or acknowledge, but being the <hi>Kings decree</hi> enforced to caſt him out, the Kings daughter is directed by the Lord to pitty, him for the preſent, and to provide to haue him nur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and nurtured, as her owne ſon, by adoption, for time to come.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> being thus adopted by her, and nurſed, (by his owne mother as the almighty did order and manage it) she tooke further care and order for his education ſoe, as he might be made meete for ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and advancement in her fathers houſe and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice; whereas she might haue brought him vp, in ſome baſe and ſervile manner, according to the qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of a <hi>captives</hi> childe, yea, and the Lord filled him with vnderſtanding and capacity to become furni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:20806:12"/> in <hi>all the learning of the Egyptians.</hi>
               <note place="margin"> Act 7.22</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> 
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> being thus qualifyed, he came to eminency and grew great in court; <hi>Pharaoh</hi> not refuſing to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre him, though he could not but (in all likely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood) know him to be an <hi>Ebrew</hi> childe; and his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferment ſeeme's to be to ſome great office of worth, and revenew, and that brought him in abandance of wealth; why elſe, are the treaſures of Egypt (on <hi>Moſes</hi> part) oppoſed to the reproach of Chriſt? it may be he was <hi>Lord Treaſurer of Egypt.</hi> (who can tell the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary?) </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> 
               <hi>Fourthly,</hi> being thus inveſted into honour,
<note place="margin"> Act 7.48</note> and wealth, he continued therein for no ſmall time, but full <hi>forty yeares,</hi> which length of time did ſoe ſeaſon him in the ſweetnes of what he had, as might (in all reaſon) make him moſt loth, and vnwilling to leave the ſame.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> 
               <hi>Fiftly,</hi> having thus long enjoyed all this favour, he was free to holde it ſtill if he would, no man doth ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſely vndermyne him by ſuborning <hi>Pharaoh</hi> againſt him, or by detection of him to haue beene a baſe <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brew bratt</hi> from the beginning, and ſoe to enrage the <hi>King</hi> againſt him for that he had crept in thus farre, and kept in thus long; neither is any thing attemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by any man, which might make <hi>Moſes</hi> to be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>content with his preſent ſtate and ſoe reſolue in a hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mor to leaue it, but he might hold what he had at his pleaſure, even for perpetuity. </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> 
               <hi>Sixtly,</hi> adde to all theſe, that if he will be going, hence, either <hi>Egypt</hi> wilbe to hott for him, or if he will tarry therein, and joyne himſelf to his owne people, he could not but ſee <hi>Pharaohs</hi> tyranny, and theire mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery much encreaſing.</p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:20806:13"/>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>Their burdens heavier,</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Their taſkmasters feircer,</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Their bondage ſorer,</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>And his owne among them, (if he will neede's make one) to be more extreame and extraordinary then all the reſt, becauſe he left ſoe much honour, and eaſe, and wealth, willingly to come to calamity t'were pitty (would <hi>Pharaoh</hi> ſay) but he should haue enough of it that was ſoe willing to it, and therefore let him (of all men) be moſt vexed, perſued and op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed aboue others, who was ſoe wittles that he could not tell, when he was well, and tarry in that happines which was ſoe graciouſly and freely con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferd vpon him, and wherein he might haue continued (through the Kings kindnes and grace) the longeſt day of his life, and would not.</p>
            <p>Theſe <hi>few</hi> (with ſome others moe, that might be inſtanced) being layd together on a heape, doe make vp mighty evidence in the eye of carnall reaſon to condemne <hi>Moſes</hi> of manifeſt folly in forſaking his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent ſtate, and following this courſe wherevnto he betooke himſelf at this time.</p>
            <p>But bring them all (&amp; all that can be pleaded to the ſame purpoſe) &amp; let <hi>faith</hi> looke vpon them, that which was a <hi>beame</hi> before, is not ſoe much as a <hi>moath</hi> now, nor worthy in any wiſe to be reſpected; this one grace melts all theſe great things into meere <hi>nullityes,</hi> and make's nothing of every thing that was before vrged to this end: neither the kindnes of the <hi>Kings daughter,</hi> nor the favour of <hi>the King her father,</hi> nor all the great things he got by both, nor his long kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping of them, nor his vndoubted danger, &amp; diſgrace in leaving them, nor every of theſe alone, nor all of
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:20806:13" rendition="simple:additions"/> them together, could doe any thing with <hi>Moſes,</hi> but he is reſolute, (by faith) to forgoe the beſt eſtate the earth could yeed him, that he might partake with the worſt, and moſt wofull condition of Gods peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and to shew it, the holy Ghoſt doth witnes, that he did willingly <hi>chuſe</hi> the one, and <hi>refuſe</hi> the other, being not forced (by flesh and blood) to either, that ſoe the power of <hi>faith</hi> might fully &amp; freely expreſſe it ſelfe in both, againſt all apprehenſions, and objec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of man whatſoever.</p>
            <p>And why should he haue done thus, if he had not knowne our <hi>doctrine</hi> to be a moſt vndeniable truth? and how came he to know ſoe much, but by the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary inſtinct of Gods jmmediate illumina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion? who revealed thus much to him and gaue him both <hi>faith</hi> to beleeue it, and <hi>conſcience</hi> to doe it accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly, in ſpyte of whatſoever might be ſuggeſted to the contrary. And why should not we fully aſſent to the truth herof, ſeing <hi>God</hi> hath gone before vs in diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covering and this man of <hi>God</hi> in doing, the ſame? eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially ſeing beſides <hi>Moſes</hi> practiſe, <hi>Gods</hi> approbation, doth warrant vs; the Lord hath ſet to his hand (as it were) and confirmed, and commended this act of <hi>Moſes</hi> vnto vs, as a fruit of that holynes and piety, which <hi>was</hi> in him, and <hi>should</hi> be in vs, who are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded to follow the faith of ſuch, as (by <hi>God)</hi> are well reported of vnto vs, as this man is, who hath a moſt ſavoury name, in the middeſt of this ſacred ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talogue, wherein ſoe many ſaints of rare note, are recorded into vs, and as much (if not more) is ſpoken of his faith, then of many others, and more of this one fruit of the ſame, then of all the reſt.</p>
            <p>So that, that which is here written of this man,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:20806:14" rendition="simple:additions"/> doth ratiſy the matter we haue in hand, his practiſe (thus conſidered as we haue ſayd) is plenary proofe of our point; it had beene apparant vanity, and gyd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynes, not any power, or truth of godlines in him, of he had not done thus by <hi>Gods</hi> direction, who by his ſpirit informed his mynde, and conformed his practiſe, and (by both) confirmed this vndoubted truth vnto vs: otherwiſe, it might haue well beene thought, he was more <hi>brayne-ſick</hi> then obedient, and beene lead from this glory, to that miſery, by <hi>frenzy,</hi> rather then by <hi>faith.</hi> But faith made glorious things vile, and vile things glorious vnto him, and ſoe he left the <hi>better</hi> ſtate which was (jndeede) the <hi>worſe,</hi> and choſe the <hi>worſe,</hi> which was (jndeede) the <hi>better,</hi> that all men might learne to know the lawfullnes of his carriage herein, and the conſcience of their owne, if in any ſuch like caſe, God call them vnto the like courſe.</p>
            <p>Now if beſides this of <hi>Moſes,</hi> we should muſter vp more examples to this end, it were moſt eaſy, (but not very neceſſary) ſoe to doe: this chapter would furnish vs with a multitude of thoſe that haue (in like manner) done worthily, and beene famous, for this very thing.</p>
            <p>What thinke you of <hi>Abraham,</hi> how were his thoughts, how ſtoode his hart this way? was he not well in this owne countrey? could a man be better, then to dwell in his owne free land, and to haue ſoe great abundance as he had of all good things? yet he muſt leaue all this <hi>fee-ſimple,</hi> and whatſoever he had vpon it, to goe he knowes not whither, only this he knowes, that whither ſoe ever it is, he hath not a foote of ground, nor any thing at all there, but muſt
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:20806:14" rendition="simple:additions"/> come from a rich inheritance, and great eſtate, where he might commaund; to ſojourne and be entertay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned as a ſtranger vpon curteſy where he could get foode and lodging for his money. And this he did at Gods command of his owne accord and vnconſtray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, aſſoone as he heard he did obey, which he had no reaſon at all to haue done, if faith had not <hi>furnished</hi> him with this perſwaſion, and <hi>furthered</hi> him to this practiſe: had he not knowne the <hi>worst</hi> place and ſtate God called him <hi>vnto,</hi> to haue beene incomparably better then the <hi>beſt</hi> God called him <hi>from;</hi> he had ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſtirred his foote; but being convinced of this truth, and mooved of God, he went willingly out, as one that knew well, the worſt that he could goe vnto to witnes his obedience as a child of God, would proue more happy to him, then all he could enjoy and poſeſſe vpon others tearmes.</p>
            <p>It were but a fruitleſſe filling vp of time, to adde more examples to a thing ſoe evident, and vndenia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble as this truth is, we will therefore paſſe from theſe, to the <hi>reaſons</hi> of the doctrine, to vnderſtand why theſe things are ſoe, and how they come to paſſe; and herevnto we haue the more <hi>reaſon,</hi> becauſe this that we teach, ſeemeth to be againſt all <hi>reaſon,</hi> and ſence, that man can commonly conceive.</p>
            <p>I doe freely profeſſe when <hi>first</hi> I apprehended it in my hart, it appeared like a ſtrang <hi>Paradoxe</hi> to my ſelf, a point, incapable of truth, jmpoſſible to be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeved; and therefore I doe not wonder that it should be ſoe hard of digeſtion to corrupt nature, and carnall reaſon, and that it will not downe with ſoe many: <hi>Nature</hi> cannot entertaine it, it is <hi>grace</hi> that muſt firſt rectify nature, and then certify it herof.
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:20806:15"/> The Lord never put this opinion into any mans hart, nor vrged the practiſe of it at his hand, before he had refyned his vnderſtanding from the droſſe and dotage, ignorance, and error, wherewith it ſtand's defiled by <hi>corrupt</hi> nature: let vs then ſtop the <hi>mouth,</hi> yea, the <hi>breath,</hi> of flesh and blood, and open the paſſages of the ſpirit of God, and giue free vent vnto them, and they will ſoone shew vs the way (and that by good reaſon too) to be throughly poſeſſed of this point of truth, and that it is moſt worthy to be creddited of vs, and embraced by vs.</p>
            <p>And the reaſons inducing vs herevnto, doe ariſe out of the due conſideration, of a <hi>double concluſion,</hi> which we will propound and proue vnto you, that you may carry them in mynde evermore, as <hi>golden</hi> &amp; moſt precious remembrances, worthy to be engra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven deepely and perpetually, in our harts, that nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Satan,</hi> nor the world, might ever raze them out, but that they might remayne with vs all our dayes,
<note place="margin"> Two Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſions.</note> even till death. And the <hi>concluſions</hi> are theſe <hi>two.</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> 1. Noe eſtate can be <hi>evill</hi> to a childe of God, but even his worſt, is <hi>good</hi> for him, yea <hi>beſt</hi> vnto him.</item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 2. Noe eſtate can be <hi>good</hi> to a wicked man, but even his <hi>best</hi> is evill to him, yea <hi>worst</hi> for him.</item>
            </list>
            <p>The very <hi>worst</hi> proue's well to a godly man, and <hi>bad</hi> is the <hi>best,</hi> to the vngodly. And in the cleare confirmation of theſe two <hi>concluſions,</hi> the reaſons of our doctrine will moſt evidently ariſe vnto vs, for it cannot but follow, yea flow moſt naturally in the courſe of all ſound argumentation, that, if the one's <hi>evill</hi> be <hi>good</hi> to him, and the others <hi>good</hi> become <hi>evill</hi> to him, then muſt the meaneſt eſtate of the former, be much more excellent, then the greateſt happines of the latter.</p>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:20806:15"/>
            <p>Now either of theſe <hi>Concluſions</hi> reſteth vpon vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deniable prooffe and demonſtration,</p>
            <p>For the <hi>firſt</hi> thus:
<note place="margin"> 1. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion. Prooved.</note> That eſtate which cometh vnto a childe of God, accompanied with the infinite loue wiſdome, goodnes, and power of God, muſt neede's be beſt vnto him: But his worſt eſtate cometh thus vpon him: Therefore it muſt needes be beſt to him. Nothing here is ſo much as queſtionable; for ſence ſayes the <hi>firſt</hi> propoſition is true, that what come's ſoe, come's well. And the <hi>word</hi> of <hi>God</hi> in the evidence thereof, and the <hi>worke</hi> of <hi>God</hi> in the experience there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, vpon all his afflicted one's, ſaith the <hi>ſecond</hi> is as true; the <hi>third</hi> (then) muſt iſſue vndoubtedly out of them <hi>both.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Againe, that eſtate which worketh towards the furtherance of our <hi>beſt good of all,</hi> muſt needes be beſt for vs; But the worſt, the moſt wofull, and diſtreſſed ſtate of every childe of God doth worke for the <hi>best:</hi> therefore it is <hi>best</hi> for him. In this argument all is ſound, for no man can doubt of the <hi>first</hi> propoſition, and the Apoſtle putt's the <hi>ſecond</hi> out of doubt, where he ſaith <hi>[All things,</hi>
               <note place="margin"> Ro. 8.28.</note> (and there he comprehend's the worſt things the world can yeeld) <hi>worke together for the best:]</hi> the <hi>concluſion</hi> then come's in of it ſelfe. And ſoe the <hi>firſt</hi> ground is cleare.</p>
            <p>For the <hi>ſecond</hi> thus.
<note place="margin"> 2. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion. Prooved.</note> That eſtate which doth ſoe harden mans hart, that he becometh thereby leaſt capable of <hi>mercy,</hi> and moſt lyable to <hi>justice,</hi> (and ſoe furthereth his vtmoſt confuſion, and eternall over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw) muſt of neceſſity be the <hi>worſt</hi> for a man that may bee: But a wicked mans <hi>beſt</hi> eſtate doth thus: Therefore even his <hi>beſt</hi> eſtate is miſerable to him. No man can with any colour queſtion the <hi>first</hi> propoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion;
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:20806:16"/> and God giue's vs ſound confirmation of the <hi>ſecond,</hi>
               <note place="margin"> Pro. 1.32</note> where he ſaith <hi>[eaſe ſtayeth the foolish, and the proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of fooles destroyeth them:]</hi> here, by the <hi>[foole]</hi> we muſt vnderſtand the vngodly man, and by <hi>[proſperity]</hi> all that which he judgeth moſt happy to himſelf in this life. Now if nothing bring a wicked man ſooner to deſtruction then that which he moſt affecteth, and deſireth; ſurely, the ſame is <hi>worſt</hi> of all for him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Againe,</hi> that muſt neede's be a mans worſt eſtate which is <hi>moſt accurſed</hi> of God to a man: But a wicked mans <hi>beſt</hi> eſtate is <hi>most accurſed</hi> of God vnto him: The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>refore his <hi>beſt</hi> eſtate cannot be but <hi>worſt</hi> vnto him. The <hi>firſt</hi> propoſition is eaſy, and evident (of it ſelf) to be beleeved:
<note place="margin"> Deu. 28.17.18.</note> The <hi>ſecond</hi> is avouched by <hi>Moſes,</hi> where he curſeth in the name of the Lord <hi>[all the, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe, and ſtore, and fruit of a wicked man, whether of his body, or beaſt, or ground]</hi> now if his encreaſe be accurſed, then the more he hath, the more accurſed he is, and as either himſelfe, or any thing he hath aboundeth, ſoe doth the curſe of God abound with it; if he grow from <hi>hundreths</hi> to <hi>thouſands,</hi> ſoe alſo doe his curſes multiply from the Lord who hath <hi>curſed the bleſſings</hi> of every vngodly perſon.
<note place="margin"> Mal. 2.2.</note> And it is to be marked, <hi>(as a moſt remarkeable curſe)</hi> that he is not curſed in the want of fruit,<note place="margin" type="runSum">Note.</note> or barrennes of his body, beaſts, or ground, for that would every common man account a curſe indeede, but, he is accurſed in the poſeſſion, and proſperity, and growth of theſe things; and this is a more <hi>wofull,</hi> by how much it is a more <hi>wonderfull</hi> curſe, that a man should haue ſoe much, and be ſoe much the more vnhappy by having it. So then, if thus it be, then is a wicked mans <hi>beſt</hi> eſtate <hi>worſt</hi> for him, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is moſt accurſed to him.</p>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:20806:16"/>
            <p>And thus theſe <hi>two concluſions</hi> ſtand vpon cleare and vnqueſtionable grounds, and are jmpregnable tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thes, and being ſoe, our mayne <hi>doctrine</hi> muſt needes iſſue from them both, as naturally as water from a fountaine; and that thus.</p>
            <p>If no eſtate can be evill vnto a <hi>good man</hi> but even his <hi>worst</hi> is good vnto him; and (on the contrary) if no eſtate can be good to a <hi>wicked man,</hi> but even his <hi>best</hi> is evill to him; why then, it muſt needes come to paſſe, that the <hi>worſt</hi> eſtate of Gods childe is <hi>better</hi> then the beſt of any wicked man: But both theſe haue beene abundantly prooved, and therefore the truth we teach, is fully confirmed; for can any man ſoe much as once doubt at all, whether the meaneſt <hi>good</hi> eſtate be to be preferred to the greateſt that is <hi>evill?</hi> or demurre whether he should chuſe of the <hi>two,</hi> (if he were put to it) <hi>a poore</hi> and perplexed condition which may helpe him to heaven, or a proſperous and <hi>opulent</hi> eſtate, which would haſten him to hell? Cear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainely this queſtion would ſoone be aſſoyled, if it were put to any man (had he but common ſence) to be determined, for even naturall reaſon would giue quick reſolution, that the <hi>worſt</hi> of that whereby a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> might be happy, were to be choſen and preferred, before the beſt of that which will procure a mans miſery.</p>
            <p>Why then, the <hi>worſt</hi> of the one being <hi>ſoe good,</hi> and the <hi>beſt</hi> of the other <hi>ſoe bad,</hi> we cannot but yeeld to our <hi>doctrine,</hi> being overcome by vndeniable evidence both of example, in him that hath tryed both eſtates by his owne experience; and of reaſon, approoving that which he (vpon tryall) had practiſed in refuſing the <hi>beſt</hi> of the one, to chooſe the <hi>worſt</hi> of the other.
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:20806:17"/> So that if we will beleeue either <hi>Moſes</hi> (who is the man that hath done it) to evidence the truth of his faith, or <hi>God,</hi> who hath magnifyed <hi>Moſes</hi> in that which he hath done, to be truly faithfull, our myndes muſt be throughly ſetled in the aſſured perſwaſion of what we haue ſoe plainely propounded, and prooved ſoe plentifully, and hold it faſt vnto our owne harts, as our duty to doe the like, if the Lord shall caſt any the like occaſion vpon vs, and call vs forth, to try, and declare our faith, by being put to the practiſe of this truth, to ſee whether we will ſoe eſteeme the reproach of <hi>Christ,</hi> and the perſecution of the ſaints, that we will giue over and abandon, the riches of the earth, and <hi>the pleaſures of ſin,</hi> to embrace the bitternes of thoſe that are beloved of <hi>God,</hi> before the ſweeteſt delicates of thoſe who are abhorred of him. A time may come, when it may be our turne either to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouch this doctrine by our conformity therevnto, or deny the Lord who hath avouched it to be his truth. And curſed are they who ſtand convinced in <hi>conſcience,</hi> of any truth of God, wherevnto they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe to yeelde <hi>obedience.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We should doe well then to doe (as the wiſe man ſaith all wiſe men doe) to wit,
<note place="margin"> Pro. 10.14.</note> 
               <hi>[lay vp knowledg]</hi> even the knowledg of this particuler, to bring it into practiſe, that our good works ſuitable to it, may make good, this word of God which hath shewed it to vs, and that therein, every man may become a <hi>Moſes,</hi> to be thus faithfull before the Lord, as he was, in this thing.</p>
            <p>And that we may be the better brought vnto it, and haue our naughty harts the more happily pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voked to the holy purpoſe of this heavenly practiſe;
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:20806:17" rendition="simple:additions"/> let vs now proceede from the apparant proofe of the point, to the powerfull application of the ſame, vnto all ſuch, vnto whome it doth, or may any way appertaine: <hi>that is,</hi> all ſorts of men, both <hi>good</hi> and <hi>bad, ſaints</hi> and <hi>ſinners;</hi> ſomething it hath to ſay vnto either of them <hi>ſeverally,</hi> a ſunder, and ſomething to them both, <hi>joyntly</hi> together. There is very litle truth (if a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny at all) that <hi>God</hi> revealeth, but it looke's every way, and is of ſome jmportant conſequence to all perſons whatſoever, if the ſappe and juyce of it be preſſed and wrung out, as it ought to be.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>1</label> Let vs then in the <hi>first</hi> place conſider of what vſe it is to Gods owne people,
<note place="margin"> Comfort to Gods children.</note> and what fruit of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort his bleſſed and beloved ones, doe receiue from the ſacred truth which we haue ſowen, for nothing but heavenly joy, &amp; ſweete conſolation, can be rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped and carryed in, to them from any thing which the Lord hath revealed from heaven; for it is writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, <hi>[light is, ſowen for the righteous,
<note place="margin"> Pſ. 97.11</note> and joy for the vpright in hart.]</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And (to ſpeake as the truth is) what childe of God can ſpeake of this truth, or heare of it being ſpoken, without ſolace to his very ſoule, if he haue faith to beleeue the ſame? ceartainly, if we be not comforted by it, it is only becauſe we are not confirmed in it; were we well reſolved of it, we could not but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce in the aſſurance therof.</p>
            <p>For why? what is it that trouble's and perplexe's a childe of God, but his preſent eſtate of miſery and diſtreſſe; and the worſe a mans miſery is, the more wofull is our diſtraction through the ſame, and when it come's to the <hi>worſt,</hi> many times we grow from di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraction to deſperation, and begin to throw our
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:20806:18"/> ſelues into forlorne and hopeles and infernall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceits touching our preſent condition, and to giue over both our ſelues, and all expectation of ever being any more happy; the preſent clowd of our ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamity, is ſo thick and darke, that we can ſee no ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shyne through it, nor dreame of any more good dayes during our lives, but make account to be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petually miſerable and vnhappy, and to be in ſoe bad caſe, as none can be in worſe, nor <hi>many,</hi> nay, ſcarce <hi>any,</hi> (as we thinke) in the like.</p>
            <p>Now in this caſe, what can be more truly ſayd to the ſaints then that of <hi>Christ</hi> to the <hi>Sadduces,
<note place="margin"> Mat. 22.29.</note> [yee erre not knowing the ſcriptures, nor the power of God]</hi> it is only your ignorance that make's you ill conceited of the ſtate you are in, and to miſtake both it and your ſelues ſoe much as you doe; did you vnderſtand the ſcriptures, and the power of this truth of <hi>God,</hi> as we haue made it plaine, it would ſoone be ſeene, how wyde you were from the truth of your eſtate, for, whereas you thinke (now you are at worſt) it's ſcarce poſſible that any body should be ſoe bad, this truth will tell you, and teach you to know, both that you are now no worſe then any child of God may be; as alſo that no wicked man is, or can be ſoe well at his <hi>beſt,</hi> as you are and shall ever be at your <hi>worſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And indeede ſoe much the more ſweete and hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly is the benefit of this doctrine, by how much it expell's the deadly venyme and poyſon, of one of the moſt heavy and hellish temptations that doth vſually ſurſprize the ſoule of them that are affected and humbled of God. And that is, the ayme and eſtimation, they haue taken of themſelues and their eſtate, (not conſidered in it ſelfe, but) compared
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:20806:18"/>
               <note type="runSum">Note.</note> with others, who are wholely free, and feele no ſuch ſorrow or extreamity as they doe: And commonly the divell carrye's the eye, and ſettle's the obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Gods children, only vpon ſuch jmpious, and prophane perſons, as eſcape the miſery wherein to they are fallen; and having faſtned them vpon ſuch an object, he then turmoyle's the mynde, and ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rannizeth over the thoughts, and double's, yea multiplye's the vexations of their ſoules, not ſoe much that they are <hi>in</hi> diſtreſſe, but, moſt of all, that others are <hi>out,</hi> who are notoriouſly vngodly; and herevpon, their thoughts doe offer to fly in Gods face, as if he were nothing ſoe gratious, or righteous, as he is magnifyed to be, ſeing he lett's his <hi>owne chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren</hi> fare ſoe ill, and ſuffer's his enemyes, who are <hi>rebells</hi> againſt him, and no better then <hi>dogs</hi> or <hi>ſwyne,</hi> (in his account) to be as well as hart can wish: and it is <hi>kindnes,</hi> or <hi>juſtice,</hi> in any earthly father to vſe his children worſe then his cattell? and if not, how much <hi>leſſe loue,</hi> and <hi>more wrong,</hi> muſt it be in him that is heavenly, who make's himſelf the mirrour of all mercy, and favour: and then as <hi>God</hi> is thus cenſured, ſoe are wicked men applauded, and the generation of the juſt condemned.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Satan</hi> hath not ſet vpon a few with this ſuggeſtion, and there are not many who haue beene aſſaulted, but they haue beene foyled. The ſtouteſt of <hi>Gods</hi> army haue ſhrunke shrewdly, and well neere fain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted through frailty, a man would wonder to ſee ſuch mighty champions ſoe miſerably dishartened, and diſcontented, when they haue taken notice how themſelues haue beene afflicted, and other (moſt vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly perſons) exempted from the evills wherewith
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:20806:19"/> they haue beene heavily laden ſo long.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>David</hi> was ſoe deeplely diſcomfited hereat, that he began to conceit well of wicked mens eſtate, and to queſtion (yea, and condemne) his owne, and all the people of <hi>God,</hi> concerning this thing, when he ſaw the proſperity of ſinners, and the miſery of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf. Let himſelf giue vs evidence how he was ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtard, and like to haue gone quite beſide himſelf, yea to haue fallen, right downe, the divell had ſo miſlead him, and trip't vp his keeles, that he was even gone and ready to giue over all:
<note place="margin"> Pſal. 73.1.2.3.4.</note> we haue the particulers related by himſelf at large in the <hi>ſeaventie third Pſalme;</hi> where he tell's vs, how this very thing had like to haue coſt him an jrrecoverable fall, and had woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded him almoſt incurably; and how much a-doe he had to bring his hart to the due conſideration of this matter, and to <hi>temper</hi> his mynde which was ſoe migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily <hi>diſtempered,</hi> with <hi>doating</hi> on his owne diſtreſſes, and <hi>dreaming</hi> of their happines; and when he compared theſe together, (to wit, their welfare, and his owne affliction) he was in a heavy taking, and growing to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward a hydeous reſolution; even (as it were) <hi>to hang his religion on the hedge,</hi> and to joyne himſelf to ſuch as were hellishly jrreligious, becauſe at the preſent they were in better caſe then he. Neither was this temptation for a <hi>litle</hi> time, nor did it, (during the time it helde him) trouble him <hi>a litle,</hi> but it ſtuck long by him, and bitt by the bone; inſomuch that he could not either eaſily, or quickly, come to ſettle himſelf into better, or ſounder thoughts, that he might ſtay himſelf vpon the truth. And why, (I pray you) did his owne <hi>bad,</hi> and their <hi>good</hi> eſtate trouble and puzzle him ſoe much? was it not becauſe he was not either
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:20806:19"/> at all informed, or not well adviſed of this truth we teach from <hi>God,</hi> who hath avouched vnto vs (as we haue heard) that the <hi>worst</hi> eſtate of his owne peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, is incomparably beyond the <hi>best</hi> proſperity of wicked perſons? Had <hi>David</hi> learned this leſſon well, all this labour, and danger, had beene ſpared, and he had beene well able, to haue waded happily through the deepeſt temporary vnhappines, the world could haue brought vpon him.</p>
            <p>Nor was <hi>David</hi> the only man in this conflict, but good <hi>Ieremiah</hi> (a man of no meane piety, or ordinary parts) he was alſo very ſorely put too'te in this parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culer, and never ſoe neere a conqueſt in any <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate,</hi> as in this: his owne mouth shall ſay how he was amazed, and put to a pittifull <hi>non-plus,</hi> when he conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered,
<note place="margin"> Ier. 12.1 2.3:</note> the courſe of <hi>Gods</hi> diſpenſation of theſe owt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward favours. That <hi>God</hi> was righteous he durſt not deny, he knew it right well; but a reaſon why wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked men should be in reſt and peace, and himſelf ſo wretched, he could not any way comprehend: this he ſaw, that they were had in honour &amp; <hi>admiration,</hi> he was in contempt and deriſion; hereat, he was at his witts end with wondring, and though he confe'ſt he durſt not enter into diſputation with <hi>God,</hi> yet he is bold to aſke him the queſtion, and entreat him to tell him, how, and why, <hi>they are in peace,</hi> and are <hi>planted,</hi> and doe <hi>proſper,</hi> that <hi>tranſgreſſe rebelliouſly?</hi> whereas with him (and other of Gods holy one's) it was nothing ſoe, but contrarywiſe all miſery and calamity that could be, came vpon them; how this should be, he could not tell, he deſire's to talke with God about it, not being ſufficient to anſwer &amp; ſatiſfy himſelf in this thing. And how came it
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:20806:20" rendition="simple:additions"/> to paſſe that a <hi>Prophet</hi> of God, of ſurpaſſing ſanctity and holynes, of extrrordinary vnderſtanding and knowledg, a man mighty in grace, of an jmpregna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſpirit, was thus battered and beaten downe with this weapon? why ſurely, for ought we can ſee, the only reaſon was becauſe he had not yet girt on the powerfull sheild of this precious truth, to ſaue him harmeles of the dreadfull dynt of that poyſoned ſword wherewith he hath hurt ſoe many holy ſaints of the living God; had he beene armed with the evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of this doctrine, and able to haue ſayd; <hi>[thus]</hi> why? the very <hi>worſt</hi> of a child of God is beyond the <hi>beſt</hi> of an vngodly man, this point had never made any ſcruple, nor beene occaſion of any doubt, or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>murre in his mynde, himſelf had beene ſoone ſatif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyed, <hi>ſatan</hi> had beene ſoone confuted, all, on all ſides had beene ſo well reſolved, that either there would haue beene a quick end, or no beginning of this buſines.</p>
            <p>Vnto theſe <hi>two,</hi> it were too eaſy to inſtance many more (in Gods booke) <hi>as great,</hi> and <hi>as good</hi> as they, who haue beene ſurprized in the ſame kinde, but it is needles to multiply more that haue beene ſoe aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaulted, for we want not, (if we looke well about vs) thoſe that at this day, are in like manner tempted, the temptor having tryed this <hi>bayte</hi> and found it to enſnare ſo <hi>many,</hi> make's vſe of it ſtill, &amp; ever will, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of the prevailing experience of the ſame. Doth he not come vpon <hi>Gods</hi> people now, and (in like manner) vpbrayd <hi>God</hi> to them, and them to themſelues; happing to make them weary of the way of <hi>God,</hi> and to encline to his courſe? what (ſaith he to a perſecuted and afflicted <hi>Christian</hi>) is this the
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:20806:20"/> 
               <hi>God</hi> you thus magnify, for infinite <hi>wiſdome, power, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence, kindnes, loue, mercy</hi> and <hi>favour,</hi> that in all theſe he is <hi>admirable,</hi> yea <hi>incomprehenſible?</hi> and are you thoſe redeemed, and beloved one's, for whome all this (and I know not what more) is reſerved? are you his <hi>ſons, daughters,</hi> his deare <hi>ſpouſe,</hi> yea, neere as his owne <hi>members?</hi> i'ſt poſſible, he should be thus good, and you in ſoe ill caſe, and others whome he make's you beleeue he abhorr's, and neglect's, to enjoy the common mercyes which you want? How can this ſtand either with <hi>his mercy,</hi> or <hi>your piety?</hi> with his good promiſes or your godly practiſes? it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be but either <hi>he</hi> muſt not be the <hi>God</hi> you make account off; or <hi>you</hi> not the men you jmagine your ſelues to be; ceartainely either <hi>his</hi> goodnes, or <hi>yours</hi> muſt faile, ſeing ſoe it is, that you are in <hi>worſe</hi> caſe then they that are ſtarke naught; were he ſuch a <hi>God,</hi> or you ſuch men as is ſuppoſed, it would be o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe then it is, both with <hi>you</hi> and with <hi>theſe</hi> wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked <hi>one's; they</hi> should haue leſſe proſperity, and <hi>you</hi> more happines, you should be in <hi>better</hi> condition, and they in <hi>worſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And if once he haue but brought vs to make queſtion either of <hi>Gods</hi> goodnes, or our owne, he hath enough, to make vs <hi>wholy</hi> miſerable, in ſuſpec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting both the goodnes of <hi>Gods nature,</hi> and of our <hi>owne grace,</hi> becauſe he well knowe's the Lord cannot en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure, but doth abhorre, both his owne, and his chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drens ſtate to be miſtruſted, inaſmuch as (befides, the deteſtable diſhonour offred to his owne moſt glorious majeſty, to be brought vnder the <hi>diſtruſt</hi> and jealouſy of his creature, as if he were not that he ſeemed to be) the <hi>divell</hi> is herein gratifyed, and his
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:20806:21"/> lymmes are applauded, and the gracious ſaints, and ſons of the moſt high condemned, as if thoſe who by the word of God ſeeme to be his <hi>best</hi> beloved, (in regard of the many glorious things that are ſpoken of them) should (by his worke) appreare to be moſt neglected, (in regard of the many greivous things that lye vpon them), and on the other ſide, ſuch as are laden with many terrible threatnings in the ſcriptures, should confute all that is therein denoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced againſt them, by the perpetuall experience of a proſperious condition for the greateſt part of their dayes.</p>
            <p>And this was the thing about which <hi>Iobs freinds</hi> lay at him ſoe hard from day to day, and would haue had him giuen vp all, and graunted himſelf an hyp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>procrite, being perſwaded themſelues, and doing their beſt to perſwade him, that it was an abſolute jmpoſſibility, and a thing ſimply incompatible
<list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Both with Gods justice and mercy,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>And with Iobs religion, and piety.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>That he who was (by Gods owne mouth once and againe) commended to be the beſt,
<note place="margin"> Iob. 1.8. cap. 2.3.</note> (one of them) in the world for goodnes, should become the wofull ſpectacle of the whole world for extraordinary evill of affliction and diſtreſſe. But <hi>Iob</hi> himſelf was won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull happy in this paſſage, and knew well how it was with him before the Lord, and all that they could vrge, did not make him ſtart <hi>a hayre</hi> from his integri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; hence he call's them miſerable comforters, and <hi>Phyſitians</hi> of noe value, and comfort's himſelf with that aſſurance which his ſoule did finde in the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubted evidence of his eternall happines, which the eye of his faith could clearely, and comforta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:20806:21" rendition="simple:additions"/> diſcerne, through the thickeſt of his preſent ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamity and tribulation.</p>
            <p>He well knew (which we muſt all learne, and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour to know) that our preſent eſtate in this world is no good glaſſe, or ſpectacle to looke through, and to repreſent a childe of God <hi>ſoe</hi> to vs, as the Lord looke's vpon him, and as before the Lord we muſt eſteeme him; noe, nothing is more deceivable, and leſſe to be truſted, then the <hi>viſible</hi> condition of any man, in reſpect of his <hi>temporalityes,</hi> which may <hi>flow,</hi> yea <hi>overflow,</hi> to the moſt prophane, and fall, and <hi>ebbe,</hi> even <hi>a-dry,</hi> to the laſt <hi>drop,</hi> from the heires of heaven, as moſt vſually they doe; and though they doe, yet are they much more happy when they are wholy <hi>empty,</hi> then the other can be in their moſt abundant full<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes; and better in the <hi>depth</hi> of their miſery, then the men of the world in their <hi>highest ſtrayne,</hi> and <hi>greatest ſtreame</hi> of proſperity. And were our vnderſtandings ſoe enlightened herein, that we could be ſtedfaſtly ſetled in the infallible perſwaſion herof, this prevay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling plea of the <hi>temptor,</hi> would prooue a meere nulli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, a very vanity, and we should be able, not only to endure, or holde out, in ſuch a hard time, as we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not shun (as divers of <hi>Gods</hi> deare children haue done) but with <hi>Moſes,</hi> rather make choyſe of ſuch a meane ſtate, and forſake a better, to approue, our obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, then to dwell in the tents, and enjoy the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights of the vngodly, vpon <hi>ſuch tearmes,</hi> as ordinarily their <hi>tenure</hi> is taken, and holden, (betweene the <hi>divell,</hi> and <hi>them</hi>) here in this world.</p>
            <p>Let no mans <hi>temporall condition</hi> then, be the leaſt oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion to call his <hi>ſpirituall,</hi> or <hi>eternall</hi> ſtate into queſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, be it farre from every faithfull man to judge ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:20806:22" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <note type="runSum">Note.</note> to ſuch owtward and vnceartaine appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, <hi>God</hi> never built his goodnes to vs, nor our hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pines before him, vpon ſuch <hi>ſand,</hi> which will <hi>ſwell,</hi> and <hi>ſincke,</hi> vpon the shift of every <hi>wynd,</hi> and ſurges of every <hi>tyde,</hi> the foundation of his loue is more firme and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mooveable. And know, there is no happines in the whole earth, good enough to be the <hi>leaſt toke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> of his <hi>true</hi> loue, nor any earthly evill vnder heave<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, bad enough (even at the worſt) to diſtemper the harts of his e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect, in the leaſt, yea though all the poyſon and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lignity thereof, were poſſible to be emptyed vpon one man. He that hath aſſured vs that our <hi>worst,</hi> doth exceede the <hi>beſt</hi> of other men, would haue vs harten our ſelues, and ſolace our ſoules herein, knowing that the true weight of this moſt worthy truth, will overpoyze and beare downe all temporary affliction that hangeth on, or preſſeth downe in this preſent evill world.</p>
            <p>Be it graunted, <hi>(for it cannot be denyed)</hi> that the <hi>worst</hi> end of the ſtaffe is in the hand of Gods people, and that it is <hi>ill</hi> with them, when worſe men fare well, let the divell haue thus much yeelded, if he will diſpute the caſe; (<hi>truth</hi> is able giue <hi>error</hi> ſome advantage, and yet <hi>conquer</hi> too) well, what will he herevpon inferre? what shalbe his forced and infernall concluſion of this our free conceſſion? why this that Gods people are in <hi>worſe</hi> caſe then wicked wen; well, be it ſoe, and what of that? ſay, they are, will any thing follow to <hi>their</hi> true diſcomfort, whoſe ſoules the Lord would not haue made ſad? if any thing more then this, let the divell ſay his <hi>worſt,</hi> and produce, and preſſe it, to the <hi>vtmost,</hi> but if this be <hi>all,</hi> all is <hi>nothing:</hi> Satan is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founded, <hi>we</hi> are confirmed, <hi>wicked</hi> men are befoold',
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:20806:22" rendition="simple:additions"/> in all this; for why? though (in ſome earthly, and temporary ſence) we may ſay, our caſe may be <hi>worſe</hi> then theirs, and theirs <hi>better</hi> then ours, yet God hath given vs to know, that in ſpirituall and heavenly conſideration our <hi>worſt</hi> is better then their <hi>beſt,</hi> and this propoſition we doe, and dare avouch, in the <hi>face</hi> of our feirceſt adverſary the divell, or the moſt fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious of thoſe tyrants which he provoketh againſt vs; who thought to inferre ſome hydeous and hopeles conſequence out of theſe poore premiſſes, whereas nothing can iſſue from our perplexity, and their peace, by any ſound evidence, but that which wilbe
<list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Glorious to the Lord,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Ioyous to his people,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Greivous to the vngodly, and</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Miſcheivous to the divell himſelf,</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Who obſerving vs thus <hi>compleately</hi> armed, againſt his mightieſt <hi>engyne,</hi> muſt now, either <hi>with shame</hi> give o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver his olde trade of tempting, or <hi>with ſorrow</hi> giue o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver his jdle hope of prevayling, and begin to thinke himſelf leſſe able to conquer vs, and every child of God (who hath this hope) to be <hi>more then a conquerour</hi> through <hi>Chriſt,</hi> who hath loved them,
<note place="margin"> Ro. 8.3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> and in his loue made thus much knowne vnto them, to make them moſt <hi>harty,</hi> in their <hi>hardest</hi> eſtate.</p>
            <p>And now (beloved) is <hi>the accuſer of</hi> our <hi>bretheren</hi> (and of our ſelues) <hi>caſt</hi> out, and overcome; we haue <hi>woone,</hi>
               <note place="margin"> Rev. 18.10.</note> he is <hi>downe,</hi> for at the <hi>lowest,</hi> he ſee's that we know our ſelues to be farre aboue all his lymms, even all the <hi>higheſt,</hi> and <hi>happiest,</hi> they can be in: and ſeing he per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive's that we now vnderſtand this truth, what hope hath he to make vs by any meanes <hi>miſerable,</hi> ſeing we can beleeue that we are more happy then any of his
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:20806:23"/> can be, in our greateſt <hi>miſery.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And that we may be the better <hi>enabled</hi> in our ſelues to <hi>overbeare</hi> him, let vs deſcend from the <hi>generall</hi> no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice herof, vnto thoſe <hi>particuler</hi> inſtances of all kinds of evill wherevnto we are incident, and we shall finde true cauſe <hi>tryumphantly</hi> to out-face him in every of them, from one to another, as we may haue occaſion to enquire into them in order.</p>
            <p>Put the caſe where you pleaſe, nay let <hi>Satan</hi> haue leaue (if you will) to particulate where <hi>he</hi> will, in thoſe miſeryes; which he imagine's may be moſt for <hi>his advantage,</hi> and <hi>our damage:</hi> whether <hi>poverty,</hi> or <hi>capti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity,</hi> or <hi>infamy,</hi> or <hi>tyranny,</hi> or <hi>death</hi> it ſelfe; we shall ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently <hi>ſolace</hi> our ſelues, and <hi>ſilence</hi> him, in each of theſe.</p>
            <p>Let vs looke a litle into them ſeverally:
<note place="margin"> Poverty.</note> Is not the <hi>poverty</hi> of a childe of <hi>God</hi> better then the <hi>wealth</hi> of the wicked? let <hi>Lazarus,</hi> and <hi>Dives</hi> be the men that shall decide the matter; I dare ſay you haue read, and heard of them <hi>both,</hi> in <hi>Gods</hi> booke; the <hi>one</hi> is deſcribed by his penury and want, the <hi>other</hi> by his ſuperfluity and abundance: the one fared deliciouſly every day, and was ſumptuoſly arayed in purple and fine lyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nen; the other had but rags (and ſcarce them) to co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver him, and deſired but the <hi>offall</hi> or <hi>reliques</hi> of the rich mans table to refresh his hungry <hi>body,</hi> and to fill his empty <hi>belly.</hi> Now, (I pray you) which of theſe <hi>two,</hi> was in the better caſe, and which of their two condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions would you chuſe, all things conſidered? I ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe no man that hath heard <hi>all the truth</hi> that is tolde of them both, but he had much rather be in <hi>Lazarus</hi> poore ſtate, then haue the riches of the other, and ſoe the poverty of Gods child, is happier then the
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:20806:23" rendition="simple:additions"/> vngodly mans abundance; and that which was here but <hi>parabolically</hi> propounded,
<note place="margin"> Pſ. 37.16 Prov. 15 16. cap. 16.8.</note> vnder theſe two per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, wilbe found <hi>really true</hi> betweene any two in the world, in their condition. [<hi>Better is</hi> a litle (ſaith <hi>David,</hi> firſt, and <hi>Salomon</hi> once &amp; againe) <hi>that the righteous hath, then the</hi> plenty <hi>&amp;</hi> ſtore <hi>of a wicked man,</hi> nay, <hi>of many wicked me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi>] Our <hi>least</hi> doth much exceede their <hi>most,</hi> in every reſpect whether of <hi>money, meats, apparrell,</hi> or watſoever.
<note place="margin"> Impriſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nement.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Againe,</hi> is not our reſtraint, and <hi>jmpriſonement,</hi> bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then their <hi>liberty</hi> and <hi>freedome?</hi> Let Gods child be the priſoner, and the jmpious perſon be free at plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure; a <hi>priſon</hi> wilbe found happier to him, then a <hi>pallace</hi> to the other. It may ſoone be tryed betweene <hi>Peter,</hi>
               <note place="margin"> Act. 12.</note> and <hi>Herod,</hi> the one was in hard reſtraint, even in chaynes, the other might goe where he would; yet (I warrant you) he that reade's the ſtory of theſe <hi>two,</hi> and count's the <hi>middle and both ends,</hi> would rather be <hi>Peter</hi> in the loathſome dungeon, then <hi>Herod</hi> in the higheſt admiration. Baſe vermine devoure <hi>Herod</hi> in all his pompe, magnificence, and royallty: the Angell of God guards, <hi>Peter</hi> in reſtraint, and bring's him out miraculouſly, and joyfully; and this is left recorded of God to comfort vs (inaſmuch as nothing is more againſt nature, then to be caged vp, and kept in) that we might know, that our <hi>God</hi> can make that <hi>reſtraint</hi> more happy to <hi>his,</hi> then another mans <hi>enlargement</hi> can be to him. The byrd it is kept in a cage is <hi>ſafe,</hi> and well provided for, of all things meete to make him ſing; but the <hi>vulture,</hi> and <hi>kyte,</hi> often prey vpon thoſe that fly in the open firmament of heaven.</p>
            <p>Nay, ſay it come to <hi>captivity,</hi>
               <note place="margin"> Captivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.</note> (which is a ſtrayne of extraordinary reſtraint) put caſe <hi>Gods childe</hi> be taken captiue, and kept in ſlavery, and that <hi>Gods
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:20806:24"/> enemy</hi> be the party in authority to detayne him <hi>there,</hi> and to tyrannize over him in a ſtrange land: I make no queſtion but the <hi>captivity</hi> of <hi>Gods</hi> people shalbe found to be a condition more truly comfortable, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> another mans <hi>eminency,</hi> yea <hi>ſoveraignity,</hi> though he were the King of that countrey wherein they are kept in bondage. <hi>Daniell</hi> and <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi> shall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cide it, the one (viz: <hi>Daniell</hi>) was the <hi>captive,</hi> the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther was the <hi>King,</hi> let any man ſay (who hath conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered what is ſayd of them both) which of the <hi>two</hi> he would chuſe to be. <hi>Surely,</hi> if the odd's had not beene extraordinary, in the compariſon, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion of theſe eſtates, <hi>Moſes</hi> had made no good match, in leaving to be a <hi>Courtier</hi> to become a <hi>Captive;</hi> but he well knew that the meaneſt and moſt oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed <hi>Iſraelite</hi> in <hi>Egypt,</hi> was more happy then that migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty <hi>Monarch,</hi> that kept them vnder. <hi>Soveraignity</hi> in a <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan,</hi> is not comporable to <hi>ſlavery</hi> in a <hi>Chriſtian.</hi> Let <hi>God</hi> giue ſentence by his revealed word, and it wilbe ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parant to be a truth vndeniable and vndoubted. A <hi>throne,</hi> and a <hi>crowne</hi> cannot be ſo good to another, as a <hi>cottage,</hi> yea, a <hi>dunghill</hi> to thoſe that are the Lords. Againe,
<note place="margin"> Perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> is not our <hi>perſecution</hi> better then their <hi>pleaſure?</hi> and are not our very <hi>diſtreſſes,</hi> beyond their <hi>delights?</hi> I thinke the <hi>three children</hi> in the fiery fornace, will ſoone ſatiſfy vs for that,
<note place="margin"> Dan. 3.</note> for they were in more com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable plight in the midſt of theſe <hi>feircest flames,</hi> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he was who caſt them in; and that the tyrant himſelf is forced to confeſſe, &amp; alſo maketh decrees to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme the ſame vnto others, that out of his mouth, all men may know the <hi>power</hi> and <hi>favour</hi> of the Lord to his owne, in ſweetening their extreameſt bitternes; and his <hi>wrath</hi> and <hi>vengeance</hi> againſt all vngodly ones,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:20806:24" rendition="simple:additions"/> in envenoming and poyſoning their greateſt ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes. God hath many precious comforts for the <hi>perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted,</hi> but nothing but curſes and plagues for <hi>perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors.</hi> The very infamy and reproach, of ſuch as ſuffer for the truth, doth ſurpaſſe the honour and reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of thoſe that caſt contempt vpon them; for the Lord doth <hi>renowne</hi> the one, and <hi>renounce</hi> the other: Men fawne vpon mighty tyrants with <hi>glorious titles,</hi> but God doth frowne vpon them as baſe and igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minious perſons. How many pages of his ſacred booke are perfumed, with the odour of their <hi>ſweete names,</hi> who haue beene diſgraced for <hi>God?</hi> and how many ſtories doe record the <hi>rotten,</hi> and <hi>ſtincking</hi> me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory of their oppreſſors? the one goe for glorious <hi>martyrs,</hi> the other for egregious and defamed <hi>malefac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors.</hi> And this made ſome who mockt the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> at the firſt,
<note place="margin"> Act. 2.</note> when they had <hi>afterward</hi> better bethought themſelues, they left mocking, and became <hi>diſciples;</hi> they gaue over <hi>reproaching,</hi> and fell to <hi>profeſſing</hi> the goſpell; and they had no reaſon <hi>thus</hi> to doe, had they not knowne that it had beene more excellent to haue beene an <hi>infamous Chriſtian,</hi> then an <hi>honorable in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidell.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But paſſing over all theſe, and ſuppoſing the <hi>worſt</hi> that can come,
<note place="margin"> Heb. 12.4.</note> (if the <hi>worſt</hi> doe come to the <hi>worſt</hi>) if men muſt <hi>reſiſt to blood,</hi> and that <hi>Death</hi> muſt end all the foreſayd afflictions, of poverty jmpriſonement, cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivity, perſecution, infamy, and whatſoever can be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dured in this life. Is not our <hi>Death,</hi> better then their <hi>life?</hi> yea, God hath ſayd it, as it may appeare in that which he hath enforced from the mouth of a moſt wicked man to witnes it. What ſay you to <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laams</hi> wish, (and that vpon his beſt thoughts) when
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:20806:25"/> he had but the taſte, and ſeene (as yet) but the glympſe of the happines, and glory of Gods people? even <hi>Balaam</hi> who came of purpoſe to curſe and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligne them, and therefore, (vnto him) it may well be thought, the life of <hi>Gods</hi> people was as bad, as a death, and worthy of his vtmoſt excecration; yet noe ſooner had <hi>God</hi> shyned a litle vpon him, only with ſome litle <hi>light,</hi> (without all <hi>life</hi>) of this truth; but the man is more in loue with the <hi>death</hi> of the righteous, then with his owne <hi>life,</hi> and would gladly ceaſe to <hi>liue</hi> as he did, to <hi>dye</hi> as they doe; his wish shewe's enough to make this good with advantage, how earneſtly doth he vtter it?
<note place="margin"> Num. 23 10.</note> 
               <hi>[Let my ſoule dye the death of the Righteous, let my last end be like vnto his]</hi> and no man in common ſence can wish any thing but that which either is <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede,</hi> (or in his apprehenſion) for his owne welfare. Moreover how many ſinguler reſpects are there wherein, the <hi>death</hi> of Gods childe is to be preferred to the <hi>life</hi> of a wicked man?</p>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>Our death is precious,</hi>
                  <note place="margin"> Pſa. 116.15. Pſa. 15.4 Phi. 1.23 2 Pet. 2.10. 1 Cor. 15.</note>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Their life is vile,</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Our death deſiderable,</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Their life abhominable.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>Thus in the <hi>laſt enemy</hi> which is death, we overgoe the vngodly, and are, (or ought to be) ſoe farre from changing <hi>liues</hi> with them, that we will not giue <hi>our death</hi> (which is the <hi>worst</hi> that can befall vs in this world) for <hi>their life,</hi> which is the only <hi>darling</hi> they deſire beyond all other, to enjoy vpon the earth.</p>
            <p>And ſoe we haue ſeene in all theſe particulers ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verally, how the odd's is ours in all reſpects, there's more to be got by our <hi>greateſt evills,</hi> then by all their <hi>best good,</hi> inſtance where you will, it's evident, in every
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:20806:25" rendition="simple:additions"/> thing which can be named, or conceited.</p>
            <p>I will now ſpeake but once more; and that shalbe of all, and every of our evills <hi>ſumm'd</hi> vp together, and gathered into a <hi>totall,</hi> that as in the <hi>Items</hi> before, ſoe now in them all at once, it may appeare, that the whole maſſe of our miſery, or the greateſt meaſure therof, that can be <hi>powred in, preſſed downe,</hi> even till it run over vpon vs, is more happy, and much better, then all the good things, that can be caſt vpon wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked perſons, yea though the whole world should empty all her fullnes, and excellency, to giue them the <hi>largest</hi> contentment, that could be wished.</p>
            <p>And we will giue you ſufficient ſecurity for the truth herof, in one that is beyond all exception, to wit, <hi>Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> who was a man of ſorrowes, a mirrour of miſeryes, in whome all kinde of calamity did com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byne, and ſettled it ſelf vpon his ſacred perſon, (con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered as he was man) ſeizing both vpon ſoule and body at once, &amp; in inexpreſſible manner vpon both, and either. It would be too tedious to particulate thoſe ſeverall paſſions which he felt, neither indeede is it more poſſible for vs to <hi>declare them,</hi> then to <hi>endure them:</hi> How was he handled, and humbled, <hi>of God, of men, of devills?</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>Of God, in justice, ſeing he ſuffered in mans ſtead.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Of men, in mallice, being inſtigated by the divell.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Of the divell, in outrage, being permitted of God to afflict him.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>The <hi>ſeverity</hi> of <hi>Gods</hi> law, the <hi>extreamity</hi> of mans cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elty, the vtmoſt of the divells <hi>tyranny,</hi> was excerciſed vpon him; betweene theſe <hi>three,</hi> he carryed <hi>(at once)</hi> the <hi>vengeance</hi> of heaven, the <hi>malignity</hi> of the earth, and the <hi>deſpite</hi> of hell, all theſe <hi>envenomed vyalls</hi> being <hi>full</hi> of
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:20806:26"/> his fathers feirceſt wrath, and moſt dreadfull indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation even to the loathſome lee's, and poyſonous dreggs, were powred vpon his precious ſoule and body, ſoe that he was <hi>all over</hi> drentch't into the moſt wofull condition that a creature could be, as car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying the malediction of the moſt mighty God, and that whole curſe, which was due, <hi>(by divine law)</hi> to man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kindes corrupt nature in the elect.</p>
            <p>Now take him at the very <hi>worst,</hi> and vtmoſt of all this evill, jmagine him as betrayed by <hi>Iudas,</hi> appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended by the <hi>High Preiſts</hi> ſervants, pynnioned, and arraigned before <hi>Pilate,</hi> &amp; there reproached blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>folded, buffeted, and every way moſt barbarouſly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſed, with thornes, rods, and whatſoever could be done to his jgnominy, and miſery, follow him from thence to his <hi>Croſſe,</hi> and thinke what he endured there, in <hi>ſight</hi> of all men, beſides the <hi>vnſeene ſufferings</hi> of his ſoule, before in the garden, and now againe, which made him fill the firmament of heaven with ſtrong, and ſtrang cryes, as being <hi>ſimply</hi> inſufferable to a meere creature, (without the vtter deſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the ſame) vnleſſe it had a <hi>Duty</hi> to ſupport it. And in this baſeſt, bittereſt, and moſt heavy condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, ſet by him ſome one among the ſons of the <hi>mighty,</hi> &amp; conceit <hi>that ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> in a compleat contrariety to all this, put vpon <hi>him</hi> all the pompe, pleaſure, princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pality, power, honour, &amp; whatſoever hart would haue; <hi>aignify</hi> him with the dominion of the whole world, and let all the crownes vnder heaven be brought into one, and ſet vpon his head; nay, <hi>dieſy</hi> him (as <hi>Herod</hi> would haue beene) and make him the only <hi>Monarch of mankinde</hi> and that nothing may be wanting to his abſolute welfare in a temporary, and terrenall
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:20806:26"/> eſtate let all <hi>mynes</hi> yeeld him <hi>treaſure,</hi> all fruits giue him <hi>pleaſure;</hi> yea thinke him as much more happy a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue all men, as <hi>Chriſt</hi> was more miſerable then any man. And when <hi>theſe two</hi> shall ſtand together (thus) in thy thoughts, ſay which of the <hi>two</hi> thou judgeſt in bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter caſe, and in whethers eſtate thou wouldeſt chuſe to ſtand; either in <hi>Chriſts</hi> at the <hi>morst,</hi> or this mans at the <hi>best.</hi> I make no queſtion but every true Chriſtian would quickly determine the caſe, and make his choyſe, and none but the <hi>Atheiſt,</hi> or infidell, would take any part with the other. Why then, is it not playne that the greateſt <hi>heape</hi> of moſt heavy vnhappi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, being piled vp together, and throwne vpon the perſon of a childe of God, is more light, and eaſy to beare, beyond all compariſon, then <hi>mountaynes,</hi> or <hi>my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes,</hi> yea, or whole <hi>worlds</hi> of wealth, and whatſoever els of the beſt things, that can be either deviſed, or deſired, to fill the ſenſuall hart of ſinfull man. Theſe <hi>two</hi> then, (thus conſidered) doe cleare the caſe, and make our comfort vnqueſtionable that all our evill exceedeth all their good, and that therefore, though the Lord, doe pleaſe to lay his heavy hand vpon his <hi>owne,</hi> and to let thoſe <hi>proſane</hi> one's goe free, and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touched, and ſoe <hi>to ſeeme</hi> to be in better caſe then we, yet now we ſee not only by prooffe of <hi>evidence,</hi> but alſo by powerfull <hi>experience,</hi> that the <hi>worſt</hi> we haue, is better then the <hi>best</hi> they can haue; our <hi>miſeries</hi> are beyond their <hi>mercyes,</hi> yea, our <hi>hell,</hi> exceede's their <hi>heaven,</hi> and ſoe they <hi>ſillily</hi> inſult over vs, but we <hi>juſtly</hi> over them; and <hi>Satan</hi> is but a foole to turmoyle vs with theſe perplexed thoughts, of the welbeing of his vaſſalls, and our ill condition, vnleſſe he could o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verturne, and take away the ground of this glorious
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:20806:27"/> truth, which overturne's him, and make's vs to glory and tryumph in our moſt greivous tribulations, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the bleſſed hope of much preſent, and of infinite and everlaſting faelicity to come to vs, for ever and ever, in due time.</p>
            <p>And beloved, vpon theſe premiſſes <hi>(thus conſidered)</hi> we ought to be ſoe farre from wondering at our mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeries, that we should rather turne all our admiration vpon our ſelues, and begin to wonder at our owne weaknes, ignorance, and infidelity, and to be wayle our wonderfull want of faith in this heavenly truth; which if it were well beleeved, and applied of vs, might and would, be ſoe farre from encreaſing our cares,
<note place="margin"> Jam. 1.2.</note> that it would rather cauſe vs to <hi>[account it excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding joy when we fall into many tribulations]</hi> and in ſtead of bleſſing vngodly men in our thoughts, at their <hi>best,</hi> we would bleſſe God for the baſeſt, and moſt dejec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted ſtate whereinto it should pleaſe him to ſuffer them to caſt vs: did we know all, we would ſoone be <hi>weary</hi> of their <hi>welfare,</hi> and moſt willing to vndergoe that condition which is reputed moſt wretched and wofull.</p>
            <p>Shall we lanch a litle further into the deepe, and diſcover the <hi>rich, rare,</hi> and <hi>hydden</hi> treaſures of this hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly truth? that by our knowledge of them, we may truly finde,
<note place="margin"> 2 Cor. 1.5</note> that [<hi>as our afflictions doe abound for Chriſt, our conſolations should abound,</hi> (yea ſuperabound) <hi>much more, by Chriſt,</hi>] and alſo, that the ſurther we wade in the particulers of our woe, we shall ſtill de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcry more abundance of bleſſed joy, and celeſtiall conſolation flowing ſo faſt vpon vs, that therein we may <hi>ſwym</hi> and bath our ſelues, in our greateſt bitter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, and by it, be ſweetely ſaved from ſinking in that
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:20806:27" rendition="simple:additions"/> 
               <hi>ſea</hi> of ſorrow and diſtreſſe, wherein ſoe many doe moſt miſerably <hi>(as in a bottomles gulfe)</hi> drowne and over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>whelme themſelues <hi>irrecoverablely.</hi> Aſſuredly if we come to ſurvey the <hi>happy,</hi> and <hi>worthy,</hi> differences of our <hi>worſt</hi> eſtate, and their <hi>best,</hi> and what ſinguler and ſurpaſſing advantages we haue of them every way; we should (at once) gather both much more abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant aſſurance of this truth, and alſo evidence of jn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comparable comfort from the ſame: inaſmuch as it will vndeniablely appeare, that in our <hi>heaviest</hi> eſtate, our ſtate is ſoe <hi>heavenly,</hi> as may, and will, (being right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ballanced) wholy overbeare all diſcomforts that can come vpon vs; &amp; teach vs to <hi>trample</hi> tribulation vnder our feete, as a thing more fit for our holy con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt and ſcorne, then for our carnall care or feare.</p>
            <p>Let vs then make our approach, and draw neere to ſome <hi>few,</hi> of thoſe <hi>innumerable</hi> particulars, which we might readily produce; inſtancing in ſuch only, as for evidence are moſt <hi>vnqueſtionable,</hi> and for conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence moſt <hi>comfortable.</hi> And the neerer we come, the more will our joy ariſe, and encreaſe vpon vs, by the bright beames of that bleſſed and celeſtiall <hi>light,</hi> that shyneth from heaven ſoe <hi>gloriouſly,</hi> in every ſeverall <hi>difference</hi> and <hi>advantage</hi> betweene their <hi>beſt,</hi> and our <hi>worſt</hi> eſtate. For you muſt know, that as the <hi>difference.</hi> ſoe the <hi>advantage,</hi> betweene our condition and theirs, is exceeding great, and beyond all dimenſion, yet we will ay me &amp; gueſſe, as we are able, to vnfolde ſuch as we shall finde moſt playne, &amp; moſt plentifull to our propoſe in ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d. To come to them the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: The firſt is this.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">1. Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage.</note> 
                  <hi>1. A childe of God is bleſſed in his</hi> worſt eſtate, <hi>and an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly man is accurſed in his</hi> beſt.</head>
               <p>Can there be a <hi>wyder</hi> difference, or a <hi>worthyer</hi>
                  <pb n="46" facs="tcp:20806:28"/> advantage then this? the difference betweene things <hi>bleſſed</hi> and <hi>curſed</hi> of God, is the moſt that may be, for God make's theſe <hi>two,</hi> the vtmoſt extreames, both of all <hi>naturall, ſpirituall,</hi> and <hi>eternall</hi> good, and evill, and the advantage is the ſame with the difference, that is to ſay, as much as can be vttered or expreſſed: but let vs try the truth herof in this particuler, wherof we ſpeake.</p>
               <p>And that we may ſoone doe, for we haue a moſt ſure word of our Lord and ſaviour <hi>Ieſus Chriſt</hi> to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure our ſoules of the ſame, Looke we into that part of his owne moſt excellent <hi>ſermon</hi> which we finde <hi>Luke. 6.</hi>
                  <note place="margin"> Luk. 6.</note> where he bringeth in, both the righteous, and the ſinner, and preſenteth either of them vnto vs, in their owne habite.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>The godly at the worſt, ver. 20.21.22.23.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>The vngodly at the beſt, ver. 24.25.26.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>The former (<hi>viz.:</hi> the faithfull) are conſidered in their <hi>Poverty, Hunger, Sorrow,</hi> and <hi>Contempt,</hi> but they are bleſſed in them all: no Poverty but bleſſed, [<hi>Bleſſed be yee</hi> poore, ver. 20.] no Hunger but bleſſed, [<hi>Bleſſed be yee that</hi> hunger, ver. 21.] no Sorrow but bleſſed, [<hi>Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed be yee that</hi> mourne, ver. 21.] no Contempt but bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, [<hi>Bleſſed are yee when men</hi> revile you &amp;c. ver. 22.23.] And (beloved) are not they a bleſſed people, and their ſtate bleſſed every way, whoſe very <hi>croſſes,</hi> yea <hi>curſes</hi> (as the world accounts them) are bleſſed? Can they wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t any thing to make them <hi>infinitely bleſſed,</hi> who<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe very wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of ſome bleſſings is <hi>ſoe bleſſed</hi> to them? Had not he [<hi>who</hi> is <hi>God to be bleſſed for ever</hi>] preached this point,
<note place="margin"> Ro. 1.15.</note> who could haue conſented, and ſet to his ſeale that it had beene true? but himſelf was <hi>hungry,</hi> and bleſſed; <hi>poore, ſorrowfull, contemptible,</hi> and bleſſed in <hi>all</hi>
                  <pb n="47" facs="tcp:20806:28"/> theſe, he ſpake what himſelf <hi>in our nature</hi> did feele, and what his members (partakers of his nature) <hi>by grace,</hi> should feele; to wit, that if the world and the divell will keepe them every way perplexed; he will ever keepe <hi>them</hi> (as God his father kept <hi>him</hi>) happy and bleſſed. If they muſt be <hi>poore,</hi> and <hi>hungry, greived,</hi> and <hi>defamed,</hi> it shalbe
<list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Bleſſed hunger,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Bleſſed poverty,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Bleſſed reproach, and</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Bleſſed greife,</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list> doe the world and the divell what they can; when they haue done their <hi>worst</hi> to Gods children, the <hi>worſt</hi> they can doe, shalbe well, and happy to them.</p>
               <p>The latter (viz: the profane) they, (on the other ſide) are ſet out to the <hi>vtmost,</hi> the <hi>moſt</hi> is made of them that can be, we haue them brought in ruffling in their <hi>Riches, Saciety, Iollity,</hi> and <hi>Honour,</hi> but they are wofull in all theſe: no wealth but wofull, [<hi>woe be to you that are rich:</hi> ver. 24.] no fullnes but wofull, [<hi>woe be to you that are full,</hi> ver. 25. no myrth but wofull, [<hi>woe be to you that laugh,</hi> ver. 25.] no honour, but wofull, [<hi>woe be to you when men applaud you,</hi> ver. 26.] And are not they a wofull people, to whome all <hi>wealth</hi> and <hi>welfare</hi> is <hi>wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full?</hi> whoſe very comforts and <hi>bleſſings</hi> (as the world accounts them) are <hi>accurſed?</hi> Can they want any thing to make them <hi>infinitely</hi> miſerable, whoſe very <hi>mercyes;</hi> are <hi>miſeryes</hi> to them? The Lord hath entayled an eternall <hi>woe,</hi> to all thoſe things wherein they place their <hi>welfare.</hi> Their <hi>bleſſings</hi> and Gods <hi>curſe,</hi> cannot be ſevered; they are ſimply inſeparable, and shall ſo deaue vnto each other for ever, that as they can laue no joy in any happines appertayning to <hi>others,</hi>
                  <pb n="48" facs="tcp:20806:29"/> ſoe they shall haue none, in that which they poſeſſe <hi>themſelues;</hi> but whenſoever they read, or heare any thing, out of Gods booke, touching any temporall benefit comming towards them, it muſt be vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood <hi>with a vengeance</hi> adhaering to it, (ſo farre as their part goeth in it) before they shall enjoy it.</p>
               <p>Now what a <hi>mercy</hi> is it, to haue every <hi>bitter</hi> thing <hi>ſweetned,</hi> every <hi>evill bleſſed?</hi> And what a <hi>miſery</hi> is it to haue every <hi>ſweete</hi> thing <hi>poyſoned,</hi> every <hi>good</hi> thing <hi>ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curſed?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This is our <hi>firſt</hi> advantage, and the odds ſtanding vpon theſe tearmes, of an <hi>evill</hi> ſtate <hi>bleſſed,</hi> and a <hi>good</hi> condition <hi>accurſed,</hi> every <hi>jdiot</hi> would ſoone determine which of the <hi>two,</hi> to chuſe; Is not a <hi>good</hi> eſtate to be deſired on any tearmes, and a <hi>bad,</hi> on none? I thinke every man would be glad of a <hi>bleſſing</hi> vpon any condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, &amp; entertayne a <hi>curſe,</hi> vpon none. And now judg (I pray you) betweene <hi>ſaints,</hi> and <hi>ſinners,</hi> which of both are in better caſe, howſoever it ſtand with either of them, in the <hi>beſt</hi> the one may haue, and the <hi>worſt</hi> that can befall the other; and according to this appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant evidence, giue vpright ſentence, whether the <hi>moſt vnhappy</hi> among the children of God, be not in more happy caſe, then the <hi>most happy</hi> among the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of this world.</p>
               <p>And thus farre concerning our <hi>firſt</hi> advantage. The <hi>ſecond</hi> is this.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">2. Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage.</note>
                  <hi>2. A child of God at his</hi> worſt, <hi>hath no true, or reall evill vp pon him, but only the appearance, or outſide of the ſame. A wicked man at his</hi> beſt, <hi>hath nothing but that which ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to be good, and is</hi> (jndeede) <hi>evill.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>And this advantage is moſt evident on either part and vndeniable in both. For <hi>firſt,</hi> for the childe of <hi>God</hi>
                  <pb n="49" facs="tcp:20806:29"/> he hath his part and intereſt in <hi>Chriſt</hi> who having ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken part of all the evills incident to the elect, hath by his owne ſuffering and enduring of them, depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved them of their <hi>venyme</hi> and <hi>poyſon,</hi> pulled out their <hi>ſting,</hi> and abolished whatſoever was <hi>truly evill</hi> in them, and ſanctifyed them ſoe, as that he <hi>alone</hi> did beare them as <hi>curſes,</hi> we (at the <hi>most,</hi> and the <hi>worſt</hi>) doe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dergoe them <hi>only</hi> as <hi>croſſes;</hi> vnto <hi>him,</hi> they were as juſt punishments for vs, vnto <hi>vs,</hi> they are nothing but mercifull chaſtiſemets: they were due to him (in our <hi>nature</hi>) by law,
<note place="margin"> Pro. 3.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> He. 12.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> &amp; became part of the <hi>malediction</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of; they come to vs, only as toke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of kindnes &amp; loue, ſo ſaith the ſpirit of God once and againe.</p>
               <p>Againe, for the vngodly man, he is miſerably gul'd, and coſned, as concerning his condition, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſomethings which <hi>ſeeme</hi> to be <hi>good,</hi> but being well ſifted, and ſearched into, are found to be no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but reall <hi>evills.</hi> For why? we know, ſin and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion did not only bring in <hi>plagues, wants,</hi> and <hi>miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryes;</hi> but alſo it brought <hi>miſcheife,</hi> and <hi>rottennes,</hi> and <hi>wretchednes,</hi> vpon the good things <hi>God</hi> created for vs, and made them evill to vs, not in their <hi>privation</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, but even in our <hi>poſeſſion</hi> of them alſo, as was no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in the former advantage. Now this curſe that by ſin cleaveth to the bleſſings of God, is (as was alſo a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſayd) inſeparable, to the ſinner; becauſe his ſin is not remooved <hi>from him,</hi> or ſatiſtyed <hi>for him,</hi> by <hi>Chriſt,</hi> vnto God, in whome, he himſelf having no parte or portion, but remayning vnder the power and rage of <hi>ſin,</hi> and right and poſeſſion of <hi>Satan,</hi> ſoe doe alſo, all thoſe things likewiſe which he doth enjoy, remayne vnder the malediction of <hi>Almighty God,</hi> and in <hi>them,</hi> he is as much deceived as he is in <hi>himſelf,</hi> who though
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:20806:30"/>
                  <note type="runSum">Note.</note> he ſeeme to be, (at leaſt to himſelf) <hi>as good</hi> as any, yea, <hi>it may be</hi> better, (in his owne conceit) then the <hi>best</hi> of the Lords beloved ones; is yet, but a <hi>lymme</hi> of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan, an ympe of hell, and no ſuch man as he made ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count he was. So that himſelf is <hi>no ſuch perſon,</hi> and all he hath, are <hi>noſuch things,</hi> as they are conceited to be, being reputed good, but diſcovered to be ſtark naught. I ooke what we are before the Lord, ſuch are all things to vs which we haue, they can be noe other in his ſight.</p>
               <p>But shall we heare the <hi>Holy Ghest</hi> ſpeake in this point, and that from them (or rather <hi>in them</hi>) whoſe experience doth <hi>actually</hi> juſtify that which we doe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouch. Looke (I pray) and obſerue, yea admire, the Apoſtle <hi>Pauls</hi> evidence in this particuler, he was a man that had tryed the <hi>worst</hi> that could be endured, and the <hi>worst</hi> (he ſaith) of that he felt, is only <hi>this,</hi> that it only <hi>ſeemed</hi> to be worſe then <hi>jndeede</hi> it was found to be; nay, (on the contrary,) that it was but a <hi>shad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow</hi> of evill,
<note place="margin"> 2 Cor. 6.8 9.10.11.</note> and a meere <hi>appearance</hi> therof, without a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny <hi>ſubſtance,</hi> or reall ſence of the ſame at all. Take we notice of his words, as we finde them, and we shall ſee this point jmpreguable: he ſpeake's (purpoſely) of his miſeryes, perſecutions, and diſtreſſes, of all ſorts, and in them all, what ſaith he? why even this, that the <hi>worſt</hi> of them were not the things themſelues they ſeemed to be, but only ſome <hi>shewes,</hi> or outſides of them: their ſorrow was no more but this, <hi>[As ſorro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wing and yet all wayes rejoycing]</hi> their poverty but this, [<hi>As being poore, yet making many rich</hi> their want but thus, <hi>[As having nothing, yet poſeſſing all things]</hi> and ſoe of the reſt, inſomuch that he breake's out moſt affectio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nately, ver. 11. <hi>O Corinthans &amp;c.</hi> as if he should ſay,
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:20806:30"/> Oh deare Chriſtians if you did but know how <hi>well</hi> it is with vs at our <hi>worst,</hi> how the Lord doth groſſly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fatuate the <hi>Divell,</hi> and befoole wicked men, in ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fring them to conceit how vnhappy we are, through the evills they caſt vpon vs; and how he doth graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly comfort vs, in taking away the <hi>evill,</hi> of all theſe <hi>evills</hi> from vs, ſoe as that, we are nothing ſoe afflic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, or diſtreſſed, as they dreame vs to be, but (on the quite contrary) we are cheered, comforted, and encouraged, that we can, and doe rejoyce exceding<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, in the vtmoſt extreamityes of <hi>all,</hi> that they are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble by might, or malice, to inflict vpon vs: if this were but knowne to you as it is felt of vs, you would rejoyce together with vs, and be perſwaded (as we are) that no more miſery can come to a true <hi>Chriſtian</hi> for the profeſſion of religion, then may remayne, and well conſort with all the joy, peace, ſolace, and hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pines, which hart can wish. And in this declaration the Lord hath enlarged our harts to tell you <hi>that truth</hi> which the world cannot receive, nor beleeue; to wit, that the <hi>worſt</hi> we can <hi>endure,</hi> may conſiſt, with the <hi>best</hi> we can <hi>deſire.</hi> The <hi>miſcheifs</hi> men bring vpon vs, of ſorrow, want, &amp;c, are but <hi>pictures</hi> or <hi>jmages</hi> of theſe things; but the joy, fullnes, &amp;c, the Lord giue's in the middeſt of them all, are true, and reall, ſound and ſubſtantiall conſolations.</p>
               <p>But now on the other ſide, for the vngodly, it is not ſoe with them: all their good things are evills <hi>indeede,</hi> how good ſoever they ſeeme to be. Haue we not shewed them to be all <hi>in the generall</hi> denounced as curſes to them from <hi>Gods</hi> owne mouth, <hi>Deut. 28.</hi> and if we come to <hi>particulers,</hi> will not every ſeverall <hi>bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing,</hi> prooue a <hi>curſe</hi> vnto them, vpon due ſearch?</p>
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:20806:31"/>
               <p>They haue <hi>myrth,</hi>
                  <note place="margin"> Pro. 14.13.</note> but ſuch as <hi>[in the middeſt wherof the hart is heavy],</hi> and doe they not droope many times jnwardly, when outwardly they are frolike and joviall? God ſaith they doe, and ſome of them haue shewed it to be too true; it is but <hi>mock-myrth</hi> they haue, lent them <hi>by Satan</hi> to delude them a litle while, &amp; to be taken from them <hi>by God,</hi> at a moments warning, whenſoever he shall but offer to frowne vpon them in the leaſt.</p>
               <p>They haue <hi>wealth,</hi> (and the world ſayes, that they who haue that, haue the bleſſing of God) but what is their wealth? <hi>ſeemingly good,</hi> yea that which make's them the beſt men, in mens judgment: but if you wilbe judged by <hi>God,</hi> who hath ſpoken it, he call's it by ſo many <hi>odious epithets</hi> as muſt needes perſwade a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny man that it is nothing leſſe then <hi>good jndeede:</hi> take a few for a taſte, is it not called
<list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Hurtfull, Eccle. 5.12.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Deceitfull, Mat. 13.22.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Dangerous, 1 Tim. 6.17.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Filthy lucre, 1 Pet. 5.2.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Vnrighteous mammon, Luk. 16.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>With a multitude more of moſt <hi>loathſome</hi> appella<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to the ſame purpoſe, by any one of which, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing that is <hi>truly good,</hi> was ever entituled.</p>
               <p>And what we ſay of their <hi>wealth,</hi> and <hi>myrth,</hi> might be ſayd of the <hi>honour,</hi> and <hi>pleaſure,</hi> of theſe men, and of all their contentments whatſoever; all and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very of which, vpon true and ſerious inquiſition, would be found no ſuch matters, as they are made account to be, in the weake jmaginations of wicked men; but things, quite contrary to the great opinion they haue of them.</p>
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:20806:31"/>
               <p>Now what a <hi>wyde difference,</hi> and what a <hi>worthy advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage</hi> is here? that a childe of Gods <hi>worst,</hi> is but <hi>ſeeming evill,</hi> and <hi>true good,</hi> and an vngodly mans <hi>best,</hi> is but <hi>ſeeming good,</hi> and <hi>true evill?</hi> Surely a litle deliberation would ſerue, to a full reſolution of any mans choyſe of theſe <hi>two,</hi> which he would haue, whether the former condition, or the latter. And this is our <hi>ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond</hi> advantage. The <hi>third</hi> followeth. And that is this.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">3. Advantage.</note>
                  <hi>3. That the ſoule of a childe of God</hi> is ſafe, <hi>in the worſt eſtate he can be in, in this life; but a wicked mans ſoule is in</hi> moſt danger <hi>when his eſtate is at beſt.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Let the Lord ſpeake for <hi>both,</hi> out of his bleſſed word, we know he will not, nay, cannot but ſay true for either ſide. For the faithfull and their ſafety <hi>firſt.</hi> Chriſt fortell's <hi>Peter</hi> of as much miſery as might be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fall him,
<note place="margin"> Luk. 22.31.</note> when he ſignifves vnto him that [<hi>Satan had a deſire to wynnow him</hi> (with the reſt) <hi>as wheate</hi>] that is, throughly, exactly, to the vtmoſt; by which words he meant to giue <hi>Peter</hi> to vnderſtand what miſeryes he was like (for the truthes ſake) to vndergoe, and how it came to paſſe accordingly, by Gods permiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the <hi>Divell,</hi> and the power, and malice of his adhaerents, the ſtory of his denyall before <hi>Chriſts</hi> death; and the relation of his life, and death, in the booke of the <hi>Acts of the Apostles,</hi> doth abundantly evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, and declare. But wherewith did <hi>Chriſt</hi> comfort <hi>Peter,</hi> when he tolde him of this outward diſcomfort and danger? why even with this very thing,
<note place="margin"> ver. 32.</note> 
                  <hi>[but I haue prayed for thee, that thy faith faile not]</hi> which was as much as to ſay; though many perſecutions, and perills may ſurprize thee, to the endangering of thy life, even vnto the death, yet know, thy ſoules eſtate shalbe
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:20806:32"/> ſecured, the power of grace <hi>in thee,</hi> the aſſurance of glory <hi>to thee,</hi> shall in no wiſe faile, that shall ſtand faſt for ever, whatſoever becometh of thy temporall part, which will perish.</p>
               <p>And not to <hi>Peter</hi> alone, was thus much ſpoken, but our <hi>Lord Ieſus Chriſt</hi> ſayd as much to all that are of vpright harts, when he ſpake that parable of the shepheard and the sheepe,
<note place="margin"> Ioh. 10.</note> wherof we read in the goſpell. He compares himſelf to the <hi>good shepheard,</hi> and his ſaints to his <hi>sheepe:</hi> now becauſe no creatures doe more miſcarry through the violence, cruelty, and outrage, of devouring beaſts, then sheepe doe, and none are in ſo much danger to be torne in peices as they, and no sheepe that men haue, are in halfe the danger that <hi>Chriſts sheepe</hi> are; <hi>Chriſt</hi> doth of pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe provide, to prevent (I ſay not the danger it ſelf, as if he meant, that never, <hi>wolfe,</hi> or <hi>beare,</hi> should come neere his folde, but) that <hi>feare,</hi> that might follow the danger, wherevnto they are incident, ſaying <hi>[my father who gaue them to me is greater then all,
<note place="margin"> ver. 26.</note> and none can take them out of my fathers hand]</hi> as if he should tell them, it were very poſſible, eaſy, and ordinary, for tyrants to breake into the fold, and fetch a way a sheepe, or two, and ſcatter (if not devoure) a whole flock; but (ſaith <hi>Chriſt</hi>) though your fleeces should be shorne, yea though your flesh should be torne, and you ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken from <hi>houſe &amp; home,</hi> yea from the earth; yet know, that your <hi>best</hi> part is <hi>ſafest,</hi> your ſoules shall none be able to touch, or take out of my fathers hand, who holdeth you faſt, and will not let you goe from him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf,
<note place="margin"> Pſa. 73.33.24.</note> vpon any tearmes; but will <hi>[hold you by his right hand, and guide you by his counſell, and afterwards bring you to glory,]</hi> though, it may be through the <hi>butchers</hi> hands.</p>
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:20806:32"/>
               <p>And the Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> himſelf tell's vs, (it may well be out of the happy experience, of the feeling of that which <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſayd to himſelf before) that the ſaints of God in thoſe times did rejoyee (and that in the middſt of many heavy temptations) with joy <hi>vnſpeaka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and glorious,</hi> be cauſe they were ſecured (touching their ſoules eſtate) of that jmmortall, and never fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding inheritance, which was reſerved for them <hi>(through the favour of God)</hi> in the heavens, and they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved <hi>(through the power of God)</hi> vnto it. In ſome <hi>vncom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable</hi> heavines they were, becauſe of their preſent afflictions, but the joy they felt by this bleſſed aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of their ſoules eſtate, was ſo much, that it was <hi>vnſpeakeable.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But now for the vngodly and the ſinner, on the other ſide, the caſe is altered with <hi>them</hi> in this thing; his body and ſtate, may be both very ſecure, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very thing may goe with him, as he would haue it, he may be planted, and rooted, and grow rancke and encreaſe <hi>mightily,</hi> in all contentments to the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fire of his hart, but in the meane while, though all his externall things ſeeme to be built on the <hi>rock,</hi> yet his ſoules eſtate is founded on the <hi>ſand,</hi> and that ſoe <hi>looſely,</hi> that every puffe of wynde, every waue of wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, beare's it downe, by reaſon of the perpetuall pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rill wherein it is.</p>
               <p>We haue too many witneſſes of this wofull truth: <hi>A whole world</hi> fell at once when they thought themſel ues firme, and faſt in the dayes of <hi>Noah;</hi> neither were the bodyes of them all neerer <hi>drowning,</hi> then the ſou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les (I will not ſay of all,
<note place="margin"> 1 Pet. 4.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> for the Apoſtle ſeeme's to me, to controle it, but) of the moſt of them, were to <hi>demnation.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:20806:33"/>
               <p>The <hi>Prophet Eſaiah,</hi>
                  <note place="margin"> Iſa. 5.15.</note> bring's in a merry crew of ſuch as neither <hi>cared</hi> for, nor <hi>feared,</hi> any thing, but paſſed their time with merriment and muſike, and ſoe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded in jollity as it paſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t: but on a ſuddaine, the next newes we heare of theſe <hi>good fellowes,</hi> is that <hi>[hell had enlarged it ſelf and opened her mouth without meaſure to receive them]</hi> as if hell were hungry for them, and could not be ſatisfyed till it had them; and are not they in moſt danger, after whome hell is thus eager?</p>
               <p>The <hi>rich glutton</hi> in the goſpell, was ſo well lyn'd, and growne ſoe warme in his wooll, having jun'd all his corne, enlarged every barne, and brought all things ſoe about, that now he was at harts eaſe, and could let himſelf <hi>a leaſe</hi> for many yeares, of peace, ſafety, fullnes, &amp; all kinde of contentment; as if he thought, that not a man among a thouſand was better vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>layd then himſelf, and that, <hi>(as David once dream'd)</hi> his rock was made ſo ſtrong that their had beene no ſtyrring of it; alas, alas, what plight was his ſoule in, all this while? Noe ſooner had he breathed out the words that argued his conceited <hi>ſafety,</hi> but inſtantly another voyce was heard from heaven, a voyce <hi>dole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, heavy,</hi> and <hi>terrible,</hi> arguing his <hi>dangerous,</hi> nay, his <hi>deſperate,</hi> nay, his <hi>damned</hi> eſtate, now jmminent, and hanging over his head, and jmmediately to be exce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted vpon him, <hi>[thou foole this night shall they take away thy ſoule]</hi> was ever man <hi>neerer</hi> miſcheife, that thought himſelf <hi>ſo farre</hi> from it? he talkes of many yeares hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pines; God tell's him of that perdition that the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher ſpeake's of <hi>[destruction shall come vpon the wicked,
<note place="margin"> Iſa.</note> and he shall not ſee the morning thereof]</hi> that is, ſuch confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion as shall ſoone come, and make quick diſpatch of all, when it doth come.</p>
               <pb n="57" facs="tcp:20806:33"/>
               <p>Thus are the ſoules of Gods ſaints bound faſt vp <hi>[in the bundle of life]</hi> by the Lord himſelf, the Lord of life; who hath <hi>bound</hi> himſelf by his owne truth, and faithfullnes, yea, <hi>ſworne</hi> by himſelf, and his holynes, to ſaue them wholy harmeles, at the <hi>worſt</hi> that can come vnto them in this world. But for the ſoules of wicked perſons, they are in wofull plight, in their bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyes beſt eſtate, and lye ſoe ſcattered, neglected, and vnregarded, (as things of naught) that <hi>God</hi> in juſtice, let's them alone to be ſeized by <hi>Satans</hi> malice, to be a prey to that devouring lyon, who will ſoone make e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verlaſting havock of them in hell.</p>
               <p>And this is the <hi>third</hi> difference, and the ſaints <hi>third</hi> advantage, beyond all vngodly men, wherein how eaſy is it to determine, who hath the better end, or which is the happier ſtate? any man that hath but a mans ſoule, jndued <hi>with reaſon,</hi> will ſoone preferre ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fety to danger in themſelues, but whoſoever hath a Chriſtians ſoule ſeaſoned <hi>with religion,</hi> will preferre the former vpon any tearmes, even the very <hi>worſt,</hi> and accept the latter vpon noe tearmes, no not the <hi>beſt.</hi> The <hi>fourth</hi> advantage followeth.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">4. Advantage.</note>
                  <hi>4. A childe of God at the</hi> worſt <hi>he can be in, in this world hath no true cauſe of feare: And a wicked man at his</hi> beſt, <hi>is in a ſtate most fearefull.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>The moſt afflicted condition of the faithfull is voyd of feare, and the fayreſt eſtate of a wicked man is full of feare. Gods booke giue's abundant teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of both; fully freeing the ſaint from feare, and filling the ſinners hart with litle elſe. Let vs take no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of that which is revealed for the people of God in this particuler.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Prophet Iſaiah,</hi>
                  <note place="margin"> Iſa. 43.1.2.3.</note> for tell's marve lous miſery vnto
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:20806:34"/> the Church, vnder the names of fire, and water, both which doe reſemble, both great diſtreſſes, and great abundance of them alſo: you know they are merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les and outragious creatures, that doe wholy burne, and vtterly overturne, all they prevaile vpon; and like vnto them muſt the calamityes be, that are like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned (to vs) by them. Now, though the very naming of <hi>fire,</hi> and <hi>water,</hi> of <hi>floods,</hi> and <hi>flames,</hi> (eſpecially to this end, to be <hi>metaphors</hi> of more heavy miſeryes) were e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to terrify and affright men, and to cauſe feare to overflow all hope of any happines; yet the Lord will in no wiſe haue his children afrayd, but laye's it vpon them by expreſſe inhibition here, (as he alſo doth many a time elſwhere) <hi>[Feare not O Iacob my ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant]</hi> and becauſe this might ſeeme an exceeding <hi>ſtrange</hi> injunction, he giue's them a <hi>ſtronge</hi> &amp; excellent reaſon for it: <hi>[For I am with thee, the waters shall not drowne, the fire shall not burne thee &amp;c.]</hi> Behold, when he tell's them of things moſt <hi>fearefull,</hi> he will not haue them feare at all.</p>
               <p>And the <hi>Apostle</hi> is of the ſame mynde, with the <hi>Prophet,</hi> writing to the Church at <hi>Philippi,</hi> (and in thoſe dayes, the times were terrible, tyranny and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treame perſecution prevayled exceedingly vpon all ſuch, as could be found to profeſſe <hi>Christianity</hi>) and exhorting them [<hi>in nothing to feare</hi> the <hi>adverſayes</hi>] (for <hi>[our]</hi> is not <hi>originally</hi> expreſſed).
<note place="margin"> Phi. 1.28</note> Obſerve how <hi>generall</hi> the exhortation is, both touching the adverſaryes, and the things to be feared in them <hi>[in nothing, feare the adverſaryes]</hi> let them be <hi>who</hi> they may be, never ſo merciles, feirce, or inhumane: let, their rage be <hi>what</hi> it wilbe, never ſoe vile, villanous, dyrefull, yea diabo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licall, yet when both are come to the <hi>most,</hi> and <hi>worſt,</hi>
                  <pb n="59" facs="tcp:20806:34"/> that can be, neither is worth fearing.</p>
               <p>In like manner, <hi>Iohn</hi> writting to the Church of <hi>Smyrna,</hi> giue's them the ſame comfortable counſell, and encouragement, againſt their perſecutions now approaching, ſaying, <hi>[Feare nothing that thou shalt ſuffer]</hi> and yet he tell's them that their tribulation shalbe ſoe extreame, and extraordinary, as if the <hi>divell</hi> were broke looſe among them, and come from <hi>hell it ſelf,</hi> to make the earth <hi>a kinde of hell</hi> vnto them, (for in what ſence their to rmentors are called <hi>Divells,</hi> their torments may be called <hi>hell</hi>) and yet he would not haue them feare, at all, though he tell them of that which would feare, yea affright, yea (almoſt) amaze any body, to thinke that their enemyes are <hi>divells,</hi> that is, ſoe exceedingly ſurpaſſing and beyond all ordinary oppreſſors, that none is <hi>bad enough</hi> to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſent them, but the <hi>divell</hi> himſelf.</p>
               <p>Theſe are the <hi>generall accquittances</hi> that the Lord hath given his ſervants to free them from all feares in all afflictions; yea, let them ſeeme never ſo <hi>fearefull,</hi> or <hi>inſernall,</hi> they are not all of them (noe not at the worſt) worth fearing in the leaſt. [<hi>Thou drewest neere</hi> (ſaith good Ieremiah) <hi>in the day of my trouble,
<note place="margin"> Lam. 38.55.56.57.</note> and ſaydst vnto me Feare not,</hi> and that when I was, <hi>in the low dun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geon.</hi>] [<hi>Though I walke in the valey of the shaddow of death,</hi> (that is, in the moſt diſcomfortable ſtate of death it ſelf) yet I will <hi>feare noe evill</hi>] ſaith good David.
<note place="margin"> Pſ. 23.4.</note> And (in a word) our <hi>Lord Ieſus Chriſt</hi> gaue this for one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong thoſe many moſt gracious leſſons he left be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hinde him, [<hi>Feare not them,</hi> (let the men be as many,
<note place="margin"> Mat. 10.28.</note> as mighty, as malicious, as they may be) <hi>that can kill the body</hi>] (be their manner of killing, as tyrannous, torturous, yea barbarous, and cruell as it can be) as
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:20806:35"/> if he would ſay, neither perſecutors, nor perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of any kinde are cauſe of any feare in the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full; he who ſpake it <hi>(as man)</hi> well knew what he ſayd, <hi>(as God)</hi> and therefore we ſtand bound to obey him as <hi>Chriſt,</hi> both <hi>God</hi> and <hi>man;</hi> knowing right well, that if any thing in mans power, might haue beene juſt matter of feare, to the faithfull, he would not haue layd this jnjunction vpon them; but being <hi>man,</hi> and accquanited with humane frailety, and being <hi>God,</hi> having command over ſuch corruptions, as he knew would flow from the ſame; he forbids <hi>all feare,</hi> in <hi>all caſes,</hi> becauſe no ſuch feare in vs, can conſiſt with the freedome of his graces;
<note place="margin"> 1. Ioh.</note> for as true <hi>loue,</hi> ſo true <hi>faith [caſteth out feare,]</hi> and ſoe doth every ſaving grace which he hath given vs.</p>
               <p>But now on the other ſide the feare of the profane doth overflow him at his <hi>beſt,</hi> &amp; in the fulleſt ſtreame of his externall happines, it breake's in vpon him to the diſturbance of his hart, yea to the fearfull de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroying of himſelf, even when he feare's nothing.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Pharaoh</hi> followed <hi>Iſraell</hi> with a reſoved mynd to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſeſſe and re-enſlaue them vnto him for ever, he hath all the ſucceſſe, hart can wish, the ſea is holden vp for him, by the ſame <hi>miraculous</hi> hand of the <hi>Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> which kept it for his owne people to paſſe over, why should he feare any <hi>ordinary</hi> danger of drowning who had an <hi>extraordinary</hi> meanes of preſervation? and now that he ſee's God to ſeeme (at leaſt) to favour him, he is bolde and adventurous, and feare's not, but he may follow them cloſe; but you know the <hi>fearefull</hi> iſſue of this <hi>feare-les</hi> attempt, to wit, his owne, and his peoples helples overthrow, in the middſt of that ſea, wherein he ſuppoſed himſelf as ſafe, as Gods ſaints
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:20806:35"/> were, and beſides the wofull perishing of his body, the loſſe of his ſoule was moſt heavy of all.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Belshazzar,</hi>
                  <note place="margin"> Dan. 5.</note> was were he would be (you know) when he had his princes, his peeres, his wiues and concu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bines, about him, to <hi>quaffe, ſwill,</hi> and <hi>carouſe,</hi> in the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred veſſells of Gods houſe; how <hi>frolike, joviall,</hi> and <hi>merry</hi> that King was we may eaſily conceive, and how farre he had put away all feare of any diſmall acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent from him, we may alſo well jmagine. Howbeit beholde, when he ſuſpected, nay ſurmized, nothing, that might any way diſaffect, much leſſe amaze him, he hath ſuch a ſuddayne, and dreadfull object in his eye, as the like hath never beene heard, or read off before; a mooving hand, writting <hi>wofull things</hi> againſt him on the wall; and there with was he ſo diſtempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, terrifyed, and in ſuch a taking as his <hi>chattering teeth,</hi> his <hi>throbbing hart,</hi> his <hi>knocking knee's,</hi> (and the reſt of his <hi>quaking</hi> members though not mentioned) may ſignify the ſtate of his perplexed ſpirit, and diſtrac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted mynde.</p>
               <p>It were moſt eaſy to multiply many of this fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full crew, whome the Lord hath accurſed many wayes, and among the reſt, with ſuch forlorne, nay infernall <hi>feares,</hi> as many a time are threatned vnto them from him, who is <hi>FEARE</hi> it ſelf, even the moſt <hi>fearfull and terrible GOD,</hi> who hath shewed all men now farre he can and doth, and will, for ever, keepe them (eve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> at their <hi>beſt</hi>) vnder the bondage of <hi>baſe fare;</hi> she<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wing himſelf vnto them evermore, both it his <hi>word,</hi> by thoſe terryfying titles of a <hi>Iudge,</hi> an <hi>Avenger,</hi> a <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuming fire,</hi> and in his <hi>worke,</hi> by thoſe amazing, &amp; ſoule<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſtracting <hi>accidents,</hi> which doe moſt vnexpectedly o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertake them, &amp; are (as it were) the very <hi>beginnings of
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:20806:36"/> hell</hi> vnto them, wherein there shalbe an infinite and endles (I ſay not <hi>conſummation,</hi> bu) <hi>combynation,</hi> of all <hi>fearfull</hi> things for ever to abide, and abound, vpon them.</p>
               <p>And this is the <hi>fourth difference,</hi> betweene the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous and the jrreligious, and the <hi>fourth advantage</hi> we (who are Gods) haue of the other. The faithfull are <hi>free</hi> from feare, the profane are <hi>full</hi> of it; it hath ſcarce, (and ought not to haue at all) <hi>a being,</hi> in thoſe that are the Lords, and belong to his loue, and in the reſt nothing is more powerfull, not only <hi>being</hi> in them, but being the greateſt <hi>predominant</hi> that beareth rule, and overbeareth, both themſelues (and that when they are <hi>best at eaſe,</hi>) and all thoſe things where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in they doe moſt boaſt, and <hi>bleſſe themſelues,</hi> as their manner is to doe. And which of theſe <hi>two</hi> to take, is moſt eaſily, and quickly determined, by any man who is not feared out of his witts. The <hi>fift</hi> advantage followeth.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">5 Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanage.</note>
                  <hi>5. That the very</hi> worſt <hi>that ever befell any child of God in this world, was ſent of purpoſe to prevent the</hi> worſt of all, (<hi>viz:</hi> perdition <hi>in the world to come) but the</hi> beſt <hi>that ever wicked man had, was but to helpe him the neerer to hell.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>The ſcripture is playne and plentifull for either part we will take a taſte of both. The <hi>Apoſtle</hi> writting to the <hi>Corinthians</hi> (and in them to all true <hi>Christians</hi>) doth aſſure vs that what correction or chaſtiſement, we endure here, is to ſaue vs from confuſion for ever [<hi>we are</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>chastened of the Lord,
<note place="margin"> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Cor. 11.32.</note> that we might not be condemned with the world</hi> the Lord doth, as <hi>good parents,</hi> doe to <hi>bad children,</hi> beſtow many a whipping vpon vs, to ſaue vs from hanging; his sharpeſt <hi>rod,</hi> is but to
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:20806:36"/> prevent a sharper <hi>ſworde,</hi> is it not better to <hi>ſmart</hi> then to <hi>bleede?</hi> or to <hi>bleede a litle</hi> by the gracious hand of a good father, then to <hi>bleede to death</hi> by the ſevere hand of a rigorous excecutioner?</p>
               <p>Surely there was ſomewhat in it,
<note place="margin"> Pſa. 119.17.</note> that <hi>David</hi> tell's vs it was ſoe <hi>[good for him that he had beene afflicted,]</hi> which intimate's he had beene in an ill caſe, if it had not beene ſoe:
<note place="margin"> Heb 11.8</note> And what may be that <hi>[ſweete fruit that come's to ſuch as haue beene</hi> (not once, <hi>(or ſoe)</hi> ſmitten, but) <hi>excerciſed often vnder affliction?]</hi> if it be not this we ſpeake of? Or what colour of reaſon can be rendred,
<note place="margin"> Rom.</note> why we should not only <hi>rejoyce,</hi> but even <hi>glory</hi> in tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulation, if it were not a ſanctifyed and aſſured mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes to eſcape deſtruction? [<hi>Thy Rod and thy Staffe</hi> (ſaith good David) <hi>they comfort me</hi>] why? how ſoe? it were a ſencles ſpeech and vntrue, if he had not told vs be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, that the Lord was his shepheard, and dealt with him as carefull shepheards doe, vſe the <hi>rod,</hi> and <hi>ſtaffe,</hi> to ſaue them from the <hi>beare,</hi> and <hi>wolfe,</hi> and therevpon he tell's vs, that no danger can affright him, becauſe the Lord <hi>(by correction)</hi> deliver's him, from the ruyine whereinto els he would run: Better the shepheard <hi>ſmyte,</hi> then the wolfe <hi>byte;</hi> they are <hi>good ſtroakes</hi> that keepe vs from the <hi>pawes</hi> and <hi>jawes</hi> of the devourer. And this was ſmel't of one of <hi>Iobs</hi> freinds long before theſe dayes, who tell's him,
<note place="margin"> Iob. 33.18.19.</note> (and God tell's vs in him) that when the Lord meaneth to <hi>[ſaue a mans ſoule from the pit, &amp;c, he chaſteneth him with payne, &amp;c:]</hi> ſcourging him <hi>ſeverely,</hi> that he may ſaue him <hi>graciouſly:</hi> And wherein, but in this alone, could his <hi>loue vnto vs,</hi> and his <hi>chastiſement of vs,</hi> goe together?</p>
               <p>But on the vngodly mans part, you haue heard be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, that his beſt eſtate helpe's him to hell, nothing
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:20806:37"/> doth more further his eternall miſery, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the things he accounts his greateſt mercy,</p>
               <p>What ſayd the Lord to <hi>Iſaiah:
<note place="margin"> Iſ. 6.9.10</note> [make the hart of this people fatt, their eares heavy &amp;c,]</hi> let them remayne in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenſible of any inſtruction, incapable of any humilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; ſtirre them not, never trouble them, but giue them their owne way and will, that they may be at harts eaſe; but to what end is all this graunted? why, that their endles miſery may be haſtened, to prevent their <hi>ſalvation,</hi> which they <hi>refuſed,</hi> to procure their <hi>damnation</hi> which they <hi>deſerved.</hi> And the ſame ſayd <hi>Chriſt</hi> (out of this <hi>Prophet</hi>) to thoſe of his time, who reſting in the <hi>ſame condition,</hi> were reſerved to the <hi>ſame destruction.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Doe we not reade of ſome that were free from all miſeryes, and had a kinde of exemption from all af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions,
<note place="margin"> Iob. 21.11.12.13.</note> all their dayes, and paſſed their time as mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily as ever men did, (in royott and revelling,) and the next newes we heare of them, is their everlaſting overthrow for ever and ever? what was it which was ſayd to Dives being in hell torments,
<note place="margin"> Luk. 16.25.</note> even this, <hi>[thou in thy life time hadst thy pleaſure, &amp;c: but now thou art tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented]</hi> as if he should ſay, thy pleaſure, eaſe, delica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, &amp;c, were the things that haſtened this perdition wherein thou art.<note type="runSum">Note.</note> And you muſt jmagine this one to be the <hi>embleme,</hi> or perſon <hi>repreſentative</hi> of all that <hi>Great one's</hi> that ever came or shall come into hell: nothings is a ſurer <hi>harbinger</hi> of eternall damnation to an vngodly man, then his freedome from temporall affliction.</p>
               <p>Did you not heare before, that <hi>[Therefore hell had enlarged her ſelf and opened her mouth,
<note place="margin"> Iſa. 5.15.</note> &amp;c,]</hi> becauſe it ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med moſt greedy to devoure the fatteſt, and grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt,
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:20806:37" rendition="simple:additions"/> of thoſe that were never taken downe nor aba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, by any earthly calamity, as if ſuch men were the ſweeteſt morſells, hell could haue?</p>
               <p>And doe you not read againe on the contrary, that,
<note place="margin"> Reu. 7.14.15.</note> [<hi>Therefore the ſaints of God</hi> are <hi>in his glorious preſence day and night for ever, and ever, and haue all teares wyped from their eyes,]</hi> becauſe <hi>they came out of great tribulation</hi> and perſecution, and had beene ſoe miſerablely han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dled here in this world, that being ſo <hi>thynne,</hi> and <hi>leane,</hi> ſo <hi>poore,</hi> and <hi>bare,</hi> for <hi>Christ,</hi> they might the better (even for that cauſe) come to be partakers of this celeſtiall bleſſednes with <hi>Christ.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And this is the <hi>fift</hi> difference, and the ſaints <hi>fift</hi> ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage, and it is no <hi>meane,</hi> but a <hi>mighty</hi> odd's that we haue of them herein: Our <hi>temporall</hi> miſery preven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth our <hi>eternall;</hi> their <hi>temporary</hi> happines doth haſten their <hi>everlaſting</hi> miſery. What man <hi>in his right mynde,</hi> would not ſoone ſay, which of the two he would take, whether the <hi>worſt</hi> of this world, with aſſurance of <hi>no evill</hi> in that which is to come; or that which may be <hi>beſt</hi> here, with ceartainety of the <hi>worſt</hi> that hell can yeelde him afterward. Alwayes we ſee, a childe of <hi>God</hi> at his <hi>worſt,</hi> hath his beſt eſtate be hynde, and a wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked mans worſt is to come, when he hath had the beſt this world could affoord him. This earth is <hi>our hell,</hi> (even all the hell we shall haue;) <hi>heaven</hi> shall ſurely follow it. It is <hi>their heaven,</hi> (even all the heaven they can haue) and <hi>hell</hi> muſt shall ſurely enſue, and ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceede it. And this is our <hi>fiſt</hi> advantage. The <hi>ſixt</hi> and laſt followeth, and that is this.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">6. Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage</note>
                  <hi>6. That a child of</hi> God <hi>at his</hi> worſt, <hi>even in all his evill whatſoever, is evermore in actuall poſeſſion of all his</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellencyes: <hi>but a wicked man, hath nothing but</hi> igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miny
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:20806:38"/> 
                  <hi>and</hi> baſenes, <hi>at his</hi> beſt, <hi>even in all this honours.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Take a childe of God, and conceit him to be cloa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed with all the calamity and contempt, you can jmagine, ſuppoſe him vnder all the reproach and mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery, that is poſſible to be put vpon him, yet now in Gods account he is,
<list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>A childe of God,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>An heire of heaven,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>A coheire with Chriſt,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>A King, and more then a conquerour,</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>And jndeede more then can be vttered by vs, or conceived by himſelfe, according to that of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle:
<note place="margin"> 1 Ioh. 3.2</note> 
                  <hi>[we are now the ſons of God, but it doth not appeare what we shalbe]</hi> as if he should ſay, we know we haue a ſtate to come, whoſe excellency cannot be knowne here; all the world cannot deviſe <hi>a name</hi> good enough to declare it; the vtmoſt here is to be called <hi>the ſons of God;</hi> but what we shalbe, is ſuch a ſtate as can be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led by <hi>no name</hi> on earth, we haue <hi>[a life which is hid with Christ in God]</hi> and till he be revealed from heaven,
<note place="margin"> Gol. 3.3</note> at his ſecond comming, the glory of this our condition cannot be diſcovered.</p>
               <p>But on the other ſide, how baſe &amp; worthleſſe, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptible and contumelious, is every vngodly man, in the middeſt of all his glory and renowne, and all the applauſe the world putt's vpon him? he that take's notice by what tearmes the <hi>Holy Ghoſt</hi> doth en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtile them, cannot but ſay, we ſay the truth, at leaſt in part; for their <hi>full infamy</hi> being <hi>infinite,</hi> that is alſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved, till the <hi>infinite honour</hi> of the elect shalbe mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſted. In the meane time are the not called,
<list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Children of hell,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Slaues of Satan.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <pb n="67" facs="tcp:20806:38" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Vile perſons,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Dogs, ſwyne, vypers,</hi> yea <hi>divells,</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>With many other more, of the like <hi>loathſome</hi> kinde, <hi>inſpired</hi> by the Lord, <hi>penned</hi> by his ſecretaryes, <hi>recorded</hi> in his ſcriptures, <hi>preached</hi> by his meſſengers, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayning for ever, as the righteous brands, and moſt proper appellations, that <hi>God</hi> himſelf hath put vpon them, and which they muſt beare from him, who is <hi>too great,</hi> and <hi>too good,</hi> to vnſay, one <hi>jot,</hi> or <hi>tittle,</hi> of that he hath ſpoken.</p>
               <p>To inſtance particuler perſons were to litle pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, all that are mentioned by name, or compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended, and meant, in that peereles catalogue which we haue in this chapter, though they were expoſed to the worſt and vtmoſt contempts that could be, for <hi>infamy,</hi> and to the moſt tyrannous and villanous tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments that could be for <hi>extreamity;</hi>
                  <note place="margin"> ver. 13.39. ver. 38.</note> yet the <hi>worst word</hi> we heare of them is this: <hi>[All theſe dyed in the faith, and obtayned a good report]</hi> and againe <hi>[Of whome the world was not worthy]</hi> loe, a <hi>world</hi> [nay more then a <hi>world</hi>) of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, in two or three words, for the <hi>whole world,</hi> (to wit, of <hi>worldly</hi> and <hi>vngodly perſons,</hi>) is not valued at the <hi>worth</hi> of one childe of <hi>God,</hi> no not by <hi>God</hi> himſelf, <hi>who</hi> hath bought them at a <hi>high price,</hi> yet gaue no more for them, then he thought them <hi>worth,</hi> and hath made knowne their worth to the world, by the <hi>price</hi> he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed on them, viz: the <hi>moſt precious blood</hi> of his <hi>only</hi> ſon, which it pleaſed him not to thinke <hi>too good,</hi> to be given for the purchaſe of their redemption, &amp; glory. So that they are not <hi>overvalued,</hi> at this <hi>invaluable</hi> rate, ſeing the moſt wiſe <hi>God</hi> out of his owne wiſdome, and loue, hath ſet thus much vpon them, and in not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counting the world worthy of them, hath alſo plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:20806:39" rendition="simple:additions"/> (through the meritts of the Lord that bought them) to account them <hi>worthy of the world to come,</hi>
                  <note place="margin"> Reu.</note> and of all that <hi>glory, jmmortality, life</hi> and <hi>beleſſednes,</hi> there, which all the witt, reaſon, and vtmoſt reach, of mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall man, is not ſo much as able once to greſſe at; for it being ſoe abſolutely infinite, it doth in finitely ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe all poſſibility of man to ayme at it, much leſſe comprehend.</p>
               <p>On the contrary now, where shall the vngodly and the ſinner appeare? or what shalbe accounted of them, if the Lord come to giue ſentence vpon them at the <hi>very best</hi> of their eſtate? what are they worth? how are they eſteemed before him? why <hi>nothing, va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity,</hi>
                  <note place="margin"> Pſal. Iſa. 40.</note> yea, <hi>leſſe then nothing, lighter then vanity;</hi> more vile then the baſeſt vermyne they tread vpon, yea more vile then the earth which harboureth both them and all <hi>baſe vermyne</hi> whatſoever; no creature ſo bad as they, vpon the whole earth, only the <hi>Divell</hi> in hell, he is ſomewhat worſe, and by <hi>how much</hi> he is worſe then they, (becauſe he made them naught,) by <hi>ſo much</hi> are they worſe then all other creatures, who were by them, and for their ſakes, <hi>accurſed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To be entituled <hi>dogs, ſwyne, vypers</hi> and ſuch like, is only to shew their baſenes, as theſe creatures ſeeme to vs,
<note place="margin"> Iob.</note> not as they are in themſelues; for ſoe ſaith <hi>Iob, [they are not to be compared to the dogs of my flock;]</hi> for theſe creatures, God made them <hi>exceeding good,</hi> only ſin <hi>(their ſin)</hi> hath made them ſoe <hi>naught,</hi> as we vſually ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count them to be; in themſelues they haue no ſin, nor ought els that is bad, but only by them, by whoſe ſins they are corrupted, and degenerate from that <hi>noble excellency,</hi> and thoſe <hi>notable qualityes</hi> of their na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, which once they had, when they had an eſtate
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:20806:39" rendition="simple:additions"/> as pure in nature, as we our ſelues in our created con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition. Now therefore as the <hi>Divell</hi> only is worſt of all, becauſe he made wicked men ſo bad, ſoe they (next him) are the worſt in the world, becauſe all other things are jmbaſed by them.</p>
               <p>Beſides, take the <hi>mightieſt</hi> among the men of the world, haue not their names pilaished with them? and are beome as rotten as their bodyes? yea worſe? becauſe whereas the <hi>carkaſe</hi> is conſumed in the earth &amp; anoye's none, their name liue's like <hi>carryon</hi> aboue ground vnburyed, and ſtinks more, and more ſtrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly from one age to another, and shall liue to rott through all generations to come for ever, till they shalbe againe rayſed out of rottennes, to liue and meete their living <hi>loathſome</hi> names before the Lords judgments ſeate, who shall then, and there, put an end to both, by throwing both, into the bottomleſſe pitt of endles perdition, they being the men that muſt riſe (to fall) to everlaſting shame and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt.</p>
               <p>To particulate <hi>Cayne, Saul, Ahitophell, Ahab, Iudas,</hi> or the reſt of that <hi>beaad-role</hi> of branded perſons whome the living and moſt glorious <hi>God,</hi> hath marked for remarkeable infamy, were not to much purpoſe, and we haue had occaſion to note them before: it ſufficeth to know, that their glory is with shame, and that all the <hi>reputation</hi> they haue had with men at the <hi>greateſt,</hi> hath but made their <hi>reproach greater</hi> with God. Men haue heaped honourable titles of greatnes vpon them to dignify and renowne them, which haue beene but the poore <hi>vapours</hi> of their <hi>ayery words,</hi> breathed out either for <hi>feare</hi> or for <hi>flattery,</hi> and haue vanished in the very vtterance;
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:20806:40"/> and <hi>God</hi> hath laden them with heavy, and moſt igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minious appellations; which his mouth having <hi>ſpoken,</hi> and his pen having <hi>written,</hi> muſt remayne to cleaue for ever, vnto that <hi>moſt</hi> vnworthy, &amp; <hi>miſerable memoriall</hi> which the world hath of them, who knowe's them by no names, or titles, but only by thoſe that are worſe then <hi>none at all.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And touching both (in this laſt difference) it may be well and ſafely obſerved, that the <hi>worſe words</hi> the world hath given Gods ſaints, the <hi>better</hi> and <hi>more glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious titles</hi> are given them of <hi>God</hi> himſelf: and the more men haue renowned the other, the more hath the Lord abhorred them, and made them abhominable, to all eyes and eares.</p>
               <p>His owne <hi>ſon</hi> (our ſaviour) when in the dayes of his flesh he dwelt among vs, had as bad, yea, and farre worſe language given him, then any that ever lived; he that reades his life knowe's how oft he was abuſed, and moſt baſely vilyfied, he <hi>was a Samaritane,</hi> he <hi>was mad,</hi> he <hi>had a divell,</hi> &amp;c: but the <hi>Lord God</hi> (his father,
<note place="margin"> Ioh. 20.17. Phil. 2.9</note> and our father,) hath <hi>given him a name aboue all names,</hi> and honor and glory aboue all principalityes and powers; and ſo much the more gloriouſly exal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted him, by how much among men he was become the ſcorne, and contempt of the people. And in like manner doth he deale with <hi>Christians</hi> (as he did with <hi>Christ</hi>) according to the eminency of their piety (for which, <hi>the greater it is,</hi> they ſuffer greater reproach,) he giue's them more excellent glory, even in the eyes of men, as we might shew in many examples. And this is our <hi>ſixt</hi> and laſt <hi>Advantage.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And now (beloved and longed for in the Lord) what shall we ſay to theſe things? here we haue had
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:20806:40" rendition="simple:additions"/> a <hi>short,</hi> and <hi>ſummary</hi> ſurvey of thoſe ſinguler, and ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſtiall advantages, that the Lords people haue, (even at their <hi>worſt</hi>) of all vngodly men at their <hi>beſt.</hi> I ſay a <hi>short</hi> and <hi>ſummary</hi> ſurvey of them, for if we should en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>large our ſelues in the diſcovery of them ſo farre as we might, <hi>when</hi> should we haue done? or <hi>where</hi> should we end? or, if we could manifeſt them as they are, <hi>(which mortality cannot doe)</hi> there could be neither <hi>end,</hi> nor <hi>meaſure,</hi> of our diſcourſe; nay, it might be truly ſayd of theſe excellent things, as the <hi>Evangelist</hi> ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth of the reſt of the acts, and ſayings of Chriſt, which are vnwritten,
<note place="margin"> Ioh. 21.25.</note> that <hi>[the whole world would not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne the bookes, &amp;c,]</hi> that muſt contayne, the full de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration of thoſe infinite things, wherein the true comfort of the ſaints doth conſiſt; for they are (in truth) <hi>vnvtterable,</hi> nay indeede, <hi>vnſearchable,</hi> as the <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postle</hi> doth plainely ſignify when he ſaith <hi>he heard (being wrapt into the third heaven) things not to be vttered.]</hi> And if of the myſteryes and ſecrets of the goſpell (which elſwhere he ſpeaketh of,) much more may it be moſt truly ſayd of the conſolation, benefit, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward of the <hi>faithfull</hi> and <hi>perſecuted</hi> profeſſors of the ſame, that they are ſuch <hi>[as eye hath not ſeene,
<note place="margin"> 1 Cor. 2.9</note> eare hath not heard, nor haue entred into the hart of man to apprehend,]</hi> the <hi>naturall</hi> man is meant in the former, the <hi>ſpirituall,</hi> may be vnderſtood in the latter: For <hi>grace</hi> is as vnable (mixt with infirmity) to comprehend <hi>heavenly</hi> things that are <hi>glorious,</hi> as <hi>nature</hi> (voyd of grace) is, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive aright and reach, thoſe that be <hi>holy</hi> and <hi>gracious.</hi> Why then, what shall we ſay to theſe heavenly things, thus <hi>heaped</hi> vp together, to make vs wholy hap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>py? if the Lord haue layd them vp in <hi>his booke</hi> should not we lay them vp in <hi>our boſomes?</hi> &amp; bleſſe him abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:20806:41"/> who hath ſoe over abundantly bleſſed vs with theſe benedictions, which are ſent vs, ſoe to ſweeten the bittereſt cup of our calamity, that we might drinke the bottome of it with all cheerfullnes and rejoycing? what ſayd the good Prophet of God once, in a caſe of this kinde, <hi>[Rejoyce O heaven, and be joyfull O earth, breake forth into prayſes O yee mountaines for the Lord hath comforted his people, and shewed mercy vpon his afflicted]</hi> and even this, may and ought all Gods people now to ſpeake (conſidering the pemiſſes) in the particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers that we haue revealed.</p>
               <p>How came the <hi>good Chriſtians</hi> of the primitiue times when perſecution was ſoe ſore and extreame, not only (as was noted before) [to rejoyce, but even to glory in tribulation?]
<note place="margin"> Ro. 5.3. Heb. 10.34. Act. 5.40 41.</note> [<hi>to ſuffer with joy</hi> (yea with much joy) <hi>the ſpoyling of their goods?</hi>] to goe from the conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory with bloody shoulders, yet <hi>[glad harts, rejoycing that were accounted worthy to vndergoe the worst for Christ?]</hi> And the Apoſtle who was ſo abundant, aboue all the reſt, (not only in the <hi>labours,</hi> but in the <hi>ſuffrings</hi> of the goſpell,
<note place="margin"> 2 Cor. 7.4</note> alſo) telleth vs playnly [<hi>Great is my rejoycing, I am full of comfort, I haue</hi> (not only abundant joy, but) <hi>joy over-abundant</hi> in <hi>all my tribulations.</hi>] Theſe are ſtrange words, yet true, and ſuch as he ſaith, he hath already in poſeſſion, and not only in ſome <hi>lighter</hi> afflictions, but in his <hi>heavyeſt</hi> diſtreſſes, even in <hi>all</hi> his tribula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,
<list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>To haue</hi> Great joy,</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>To be</hi> full of comfort, <hi>yea</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>To be</hi> over-full, <hi>or to</hi> over-abounde,</item>
                  </list> is ſuch a ſtrayne of ſpeech, as never fell from man, by any <hi>ſence</hi> or <hi>reaſon</hi> of flesh and blood, but only from the <hi>ſpirit</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> and the <hi>power</hi> of his grace, which
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:20806:41" rendition="simple:additions"/> had perſwaded his ſoule of the <hi>ſweetnes</hi> of this ſaving truth that we teach; that a man at his <hi>worſt</hi> should not only be <hi>full,</hi> but <hi>overflow</hi> with comfort and joy, which is more then any wicked man can ſay of his <hi>beſt,</hi> for all the happines vnder heaven cannot <hi>fill,</hi> much leſſe <hi>over-fill</hi> the hart of man, he cannot be ſatiſfyed, much leſſe can he be <hi>glutted indeede,</hi> or <hi>ſurfett intruth,</hi> with all temporall delights, he that had the largeſt share in them of any <hi>mortall man</hi> that ever liued, (even <hi>Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi>) tell's vs they cannot giue full contentment, &amp; againe <hi>[the eye cannot be ſatiſfyed with ſeeing,
<note place="margin"> Eccleſ. 5.10.</note> nor the eare with hearing, &amp;c:]</hi> but here, at our <hi>very worſt,</hi> we haue our meaſure of joy and ſolace, preſſed downe to the <hi>bottome,</hi> filled vp to the <hi>brym,</hi> and running over vpon vs, from the Lord, who telleth vs, that theſe light and short troubles,
<note place="margin"> 2 Cor. 4.17.</note> (doe not only thus conſiſt with our great rejoycing here preſent, but) they [<hi>procure vnto vs in heaven,</hi> an <hi>exceeding exceſſiue</hi> (for ſoe the words doe ſound in their true ſence) <hi>eternall waight of glory:</hi>] loe, what words the <hi>Holy Ghost</hi> vſeth to expreſſe theſe things to vs, <hi>[exceeding,] [exceſſiue,]</hi> to giue vs to know, that theſe being the <hi>greateſt words</hi> which can shew any thing to vs, the things intended in them, are <hi>greater</hi> then <hi>all words</hi> can expreſſe.</p>
               <p>And why then doe we <hi>droope,</hi> or <hi>faint</hi> vnder any thing (dearely beloved?) how ill doth ſorrow or feare (of this ſort) become a <hi>Saint?</hi>
                  <note place="margin"> 1 Theſ. 5.16. Phil. 4.13.</note> who is not only commanded to <hi>[rejoyce in the Lord, evermore,]</hi> but hath reaſon give<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him ſoe to doe, in the things (thus farre) declared by vs. <hi>Queſtionleſſe,</hi> if we could ſettle our thoughts vpon theſe divine things they would pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce very divine effects in our harts, and put vs (as it were) into heaven before-hand, <hi>(in part,)</hi> and make
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:20806:42"/> vs much the more meete, for the abſolute poſeſſion of the perfections thereof in due time.</p>
               <p>And this is the <hi>first vſe</hi> of this moſt worthy point of truth, wherein though we haue ſeemed long to inſiſt; yet know, it is ſuch good being here, (as Peter once ſayd) that we could even build tabernacles in the bleſſed comfort of the ſame, as finding it to be much harder to <hi>get out,</hi> then <hi>to goe on</hi> further in the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery hereof, wherein a faithfull man is (after a ſort) <hi>tranſfigured,</hi> and mounted aloft farre beyond all <hi>morta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, miſery,</hi> and <hi>vexation,</hi> of men, or divells in this world; which now, (thus rayſed) either he ſeeth not, or if he doe, he beholdeth them as farre vnder his <hi>feete,</hi> with a Chriſtian, and holy contempt, and himſelf hath (his hart being ſetled on theſe things) his ſeate <hi>on high</hi> with the Lord, and his bleſſed and beloved ones, vnto whome he ſeemeth to be tranſlated, in the ſweete apprehenſions of his ſoule, while he is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſant in theſe ſacred, and ſupernaturall medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; and beholdeth the <hi>glorious face</hi> of God, shyning vpon him, and his owne hart ſoe dazeled with the <hi>hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly luſtre</hi> of this moſt bleſſed light, that he cannot well tell (for the time) where he is, whether <hi>in the body or noe,</hi> his ſoule ſoaring aloft, and finding ſuch incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceivable contentment in theſe conſolations.</p>
               <p>But we muſt put an end to our diſcourſe of theſe comforts and leaue the reſt, to that time when we shall come into <hi>actuall</hi> and full poſeſſion of <hi>endles life,</hi> where we shall enjoy the infinite fullnes of thoſe things, whereof, all that can be ſayd of the <hi>beſt</hi> things that are <hi>here,</hi> are, but the <hi>beginnings,</hi> and firſt fruits, of that which we shall haue <hi>there.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>2</label> And ſoe we come to <hi>a ſecond vſe</hi> of the this bleſſed
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:20806:42"/> truth which concerneth wicked men,
<note place="margin"> Terror. to preſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutors.</note> vnto whome we muſt change our note, and <hi>ſing another tune,</hi> from the true conſequence of the ſame; for it ſoundeth (as all heavenly truth doth) <hi>heavily,</hi> in their eares, and was not more <hi>ſweetely muſicall</hi> to the ſaints, then it is <hi>dolefully miſerable,</hi> to ſinners. We neede not ſay much to them, the loſſe of all the aforeſayd happines and faelicity of the faithfull, is more then a litle, inaſmuch as we haue ſeene, (as we haue gone all <hi>a-long</hi> from one paſſage to another,) their miſery &amp; vnhappines, hath ſtill beene entwiſted <hi>(oppoſitely)</hi> to the joy of Gods choſen, and entayled therevnto, ſo that they are not only <hi>deprived</hi> of ſoe much joy, as hath appeared to the faithfull in every particuler, from point to point; but are further <hi>aſſured</hi> of as many, and as great miſcheifs, as our mercyes doe amount vnto; every <hi>comfort</hi> to vs, carrying with it <hi>a curſe</hi> alſo vnto them,</p>
               <p>Yet over and aboue all that we haue ſayd, there is ſomewhat more falling vpon them, (to their further terror) from this truth; and that is meant vnto the perſecutors and tormentors of Gods people, who doe full often affright, and terrify, thoſe whome they haue in their power, with big, and bitter words, with cruell, and curſed ſpeakings; viz: that <hi>this,</hi> and <hi>that</hi> they will doe, and they shall, (I, that they shall) well know, that it is in their power to excerciſe their plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, and to haue their will vpon them: Iuſt, as inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent and jmperious as <hi>Pilate, [knowest thou not that I haue power to bynde thee, &amp;c,]</hi> and theſe tyrants will jmpri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, will torture, will kill, what will they not <hi>doe?</hi> and what shall not Gods childe <hi>endure,</hi> if either <hi>vile words,</hi> or <hi>villanous deedes,</hi> may put them into dread, diſtrac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, yea, deſperation?</p>
               <pb n="76" facs="tcp:20806:43" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>But wilt thou know,
<note place="margin"> Iam. 2.20.</note> O thou vayne man],</hi> and vile miſcreant, how jdlely all this is vttered to terrify him, who can by vertue of the glorious light of this gracious truth, <hi>tryumphantly</hi> retort all this vpon thy ſelf, to thyne owne terror and amazement of hart, and tell thee to thy teeth, that ſeing the <hi>worſt</hi> of Gods childe is better then the <hi>best,</hi> of any wicked man, therefore all thou canſt ſay, or doe, cannot make him halfe ſo miſerable as thy ſelf art, who doeſt thus menace the members of <hi>Ieſus Christ.</hi> When thou haſt <hi>ſpett-out</hi> all thy mallice, <hi>ſpued vp</hi> all the venyme, <hi>ſpent,</hi> and emptyed vpon them, all the malignity and gall the divell ever engendered, and encreaſed in thee; yet even then, thou haſt not made him halfe ſoe <hi>vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy,</hi> as thou now art in thy <hi>conceited happines,</hi> and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emption, from all theſe extreamityes,</p>
               <p>And the poore diſtreſſed <hi>Martyr</hi> of the <hi>Lord Ieſus,</hi> may ſay in the tryumph, of a true &amp; powerfull faith, <hi>O Tyrant,</hi> or <hi>Oppreſſor, know, that now in this agony, in theſe anguishes, I will not change ſtates with</hi> thee, <hi>my caſe is better then thine, all thou canst doe, cannot make me ſo bad as thy ſelf; my tortures are to he preferred to thy pleaſures, my racks, chay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, ſcourges, &amp;c, cannot make me ſo miſerable, as thy palace, proſperity, caſe, honour, and power make's thee: I am more jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yous vnder all theſe great greivances, then thou canst be in all thy greatest gloryes: doc thou perſecute I will joy, doe thou af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flict I will pray;</hi> ſmite <hi>thou, I will</hi> ſmile; <hi>my God hath layd a ſweete, a ſoveraigne, a healing,</hi> yea <hi>a heavenly plaiſter, to all theſe bitter ſores, which fully</hi> cure's <hi>them, and</hi> comforts <hi>me: namely, that he hath taught me to learne, that which now, I haue learned to feele, that my worst estate, is better then thy best, the ſweetnes of which leſſon, make's all evills caſy to ſwallow, and of quick, and comfortable digeſtion, even at the extreameſt, that
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:20806:43" rendition="simple:additions"/> they can be. And herein I joy, and will joy, maugre all the divells in hell, and hell hounds on earth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Would not this, (or the like ſpeach vnto this) make the eares of tyrants to <hi>tingle,</hi> and their harts to <hi>tremble?</hi> would it not vexe and torture their very ſpirits within them, to here theſe voyces ſounding from the mouthes of thoſe, who are vnder their heavieſt vexations?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ceartainely,</hi> it would worke one way or other with them, if they could but beleeue it; either it would cauſe repentance vnto ſalvation, and make them weary of their wickednes, and moſt willing to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come as one of <hi>them</hi> whome they thus abuſe; or to frett and fume, and gnaw owne their owne bowells, to ſee themſelues defeated in all the jmpious purpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, which being to make the Lords people moſt mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable of all men, cannot by the <hi>most,</hi> and <hi>worſt,</hi> and <hi>all,</hi> they can doe, make them any way ſoe miſerable as themſelues, who <hi>(in their owne opinion)</hi> are more hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py then any. Doe you thinke it would not make their harts to <hi>boyle,</hi> yea to <hi>burne,</hi> within them, and <hi>chafe</hi> them ſoe throughly, that they should be forced to <hi>foame</hi> at mouth, with indignation, and diſtemper? Were a man but in their boſomes, to ſee how they frett, and vexe <hi>jnwardly,</hi> when they perceive, <hi>God himſelf</hi> to laugh them to ſcorne in heaven, and <hi>his people</hi> to laugh at them on earth, to ſee, that all the mallice and villany the divell can arme them with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, cannot make anothers eſtate <hi>at worſt,</hi> ſo bad then their owne, <hi>at beſt;</hi> then would ſomething appeare, as the effect and efficacy of this truth, which we haue told them; it may be they would ceaſe their bloody hands againſt the bleſſed of the Lord, and
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:20806:44"/> begin to lay them on themſelues, as <hi>Iudas,</hi> (and ſome other of their <hi>praediceſſors,</hi>) haue done. But our <hi>God,</hi> the <hi>God of heaven,</hi>
                  <note place="margin"> 2 Cor. 4.4</note> doth ſuffer the <hi>Divell,</hi> the <hi>[God of this world to blyndefolde their eyes that they should not ſee,]</hi> or know, or acknowledg this truth, &amp; ſoe by the ignorance ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, they worke out, at once
<list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Their owne perdition,</hi>
                        <note place="margin"> Phi. 1.28</note> and</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Our ſalvation,</hi> and make</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Vs, bleſſed Martyrs</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Themſelues, accurſed Malefactors,</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list> in deſpight of all that they <hi>(contrarily)</hi> intend; and her: of, if they might, or could be perſwaded, no queſtion were to be made, but they would quickly become, either <hi>better,</hi> or <hi>worſe.</hi> But it is miſery enough that they cannot be brought to beleeue the ſame; oh, what ſaith the Apoſtle <hi>[if our goſpell be hid,
<note place="margin"> 2 Cor. 4.3</note> it is hid to them that are loſt:]</hi> A heavy ſentence, inaſmuch as by ignorance (eſpecially <hi>wilfull</hi>) of any truth, <hi>more ſin</hi> is multiplyed againſt <hi>God, more ſervice,</hi> is done to the <hi>Divell,</hi> more miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheife to <hi>men,</hi>
                  <note place="margin"> Rom. 2.</note> and (conſequently) more plagues hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped on, and wrath ſtored vp againſt the day of wrath, to be powered by the mighty arme of <hi>Almighty God,</hi> vpon the heads of all thoſe, that haue thus encreaſed their jmpietyes before him, who shall not eſcape the full poyſon of all thoſe his <hi>envenomed vyalls</hi> which he hath revealed from heaven, to be reſerved in hell for them.</p>
               <p>But we will now <hi>leaue</hi> theſe men, as men <hi>left of God,</hi> and not ſoe happy as once to giue <hi>vs, the hearing,</hi> or the <hi>Lord, the beleeving</hi> of this truth; but given over to be <hi>drunke</hi> with their owne <hi>deluſions,</hi> to their owne damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, perſwading themſelues ſoe well of their owne evill eſtate, and being ſo ill perſwaded of the good,
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:20806:44" rendition="simple:additions"/> and bleſſed condition of Gods children, that they meane to continue as they are, and to proceede in their jmpiety againſt the Lord, &amp; oppreſſion againſt his people, till they haue wrought out, their owne e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall confuſion by <hi>both,</hi> and provoked the dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full indignation of the <hi>Lord God,</hi> to come vpon them to the vttermoſt, through this <hi>double jniquity,</hi> commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted againſt his higheſt majeſty.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>3</label> And in our <hi>laſt vſe</hi> we will turne our ſpeech to all manner of perſons, endeavouring to doe our beſt,
<note place="margin"> Instruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to all men.</note> to giue them that true information, which floweth from this point wherof we now treat, and the premiſſes of the ſame, which haue beene ſo particulerly and plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifully related, at large vnto vs.</p>
               <p>And the conſequence of this truth for matter of inſtruction looketh, <hi>both</hi> at the ſaints of God <hi>themſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues, and alſo</hi> at all <hi>others,</hi> that are not yet revealed to be ſuch.</p>
               <p>For the <hi>former,</hi> viz: thoſe who haue beene already found and approoved to be faithfull, whoſe happy intereſt is therefore vndeniable in this heavenly truth, it call's for their conſtant, continuall, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuall <hi>perſeverance,</hi> in that their eſtate of grace and holynes, the <hi>worſt</hi> whereof, is ſo good, as we haue heard. For if our firſt being in grace (while we are yet but <hi>babes,</hi> or <hi>beginners</hi> therein) doe giue vs aſſurance of ſo much conſolation, doubtles, if we continue &amp; hold out to the end, as we grow, and goe on, in grace, ſoe doth the ſweete ſavour of this happines encreaſe and multiply vpon vs. But I hope the diſcovery of the comforts aforeſayd, is ſuch, as may ſaue me the labour, of any further preſſing of this point vpon them, and that their taſte of the bleſſednes of them is
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:20806:45"/> ſo pleaſant, as they haue <hi>ſenſible arguments</hi> within them ſufficient, both to perſwade them to tarry where they are; and to oppoſe, and repulſe all ſuggeſtions to the contrary. And therefore I will not perſue them with more words, for whoſe ſakes eſpecially, all that is paſt, hath beene vttered, and whoſe ſetled reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions touching their ſtate of grace, are ſuch, and ſo vnmoveable as was the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> who ſayd, <hi>[I am ſure, that neither death,
<note place="margin"> Rom. 8.38.39.</note> nor life, nor Angells, nor Principalityes, nor Powers, nor things preſent, nor things to come, nor heigh nor depth, nor any other creature, shalbe able to ſeparate me from the loue of God, which is in</hi> Ieſus Chriſt our Lord.] This was his, of <hi>himſelf,</hi> and the <hi>Romans;</hi> this is, and ought to be ours, of <hi>our ſelues,</hi> &amp; of all <hi>true Chriſtians;</hi> &amp; therein we will reſt, and turno our <hi>last ſpeech,</hi> vnto thoſe that yet are <hi>not turned</hi> to the Lord, by any viſible manifeſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of that faith, the vertue wherof, doth giue them their part, and portion in the ſaving peace, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, of that which hath beene vttered.</p>
               <p>And what can we vrge <hi>(either more, or leſſe)</hi> vpon them, then that they should now <hi>(at laſt)</hi> learne to leaue their former ſinfull, and vngodly condition, and cleave to the Lord in the power, and truth of ſincerity, and ſanctification; that inaſmuch as they are not yet <hi>cannonized</hi> of the Lord for ſaints, nor haue their <hi>names written in the booke of life,</hi> (ſo farre as their life sheweth vnto men) they might now <hi>(once)</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinke themſelues what they are, and come out of that eſtate, wherein they cannot be happy.</p>
               <p>And what more <hi>weighty,</hi> or <hi>worthy</hi> argument can we vſe, then this which is ſoe powerfull to perſwade, if it be duely pondered of them: For it is drawne from that which nature affecteth, and deſireth <hi>(in all men)</hi>
                  <pb n="81" facs="tcp:20806:45"/> aboue <hi>all things,</hi> to wit, the having of a <hi>good,</hi> yea <hi>the beſt</hi> eſtate, and condition, that is to be had in this world, and a much more better, in heaven, then can be had vpon any tearmes here. And can there be a better eſtate, then that? or any ſo good as that? which
<list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Is impoſſible to be had, at the worst, and</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>The worſt wherof, is better then the beſt of any other.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>Beholde, out of this eſtate <hi>all proſperity is miſery,</hi> and in it, <hi>all miſery is proſſerity:</hi> haue we not made it more then manifeſt, by ſuch abundance of moſt <hi>infallible, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine,</hi> and <hi>vndoubted</hi> evidence, as neither <hi>divells,</hi> nor men, can colourably gaineſay? And is not ſuch a ſtate worth ſeeking among thoſe to whome it is <hi>ſolely,</hi> and <hi>wholey,</hi> appropriated of the Lord? who would not be <hi>a Saint</hi> vpon ſuch tearmes, &amp; embrace piety, becauſe of the precious and peerleſſe <hi>bleſſednes,</hi> it bring's with it, vpon a mans <hi>vniverſall</hi> ſtate here, and that which is <hi>eternall</hi> in heaven? why, let men learne to reaſon and diſpute thus.</p>
               <p>If there be a ſort of people, who are in ſuch a ſtate as hath beene ſayd, the <hi>worst</hi> wherof is ſimply good, and jncomparably <hi>better</hi> then the <hi>beſt</hi> eſtate of any other whatſoever; what doe I, what am I, out of that ſociety? I ſee my ſelf miſerable (as I am) at <hi>my beſt,</hi> I will ſurely out of my ſelf, and ſtrive with all my ſtrength to be one of thoſe men, among whome the <hi>meanest</hi> fare ſoe well, when they are in the <hi>worſt eſtate</hi> that can be.</p>
               <p>And if (thus) <hi>God</hi> make vs able to begin to argue (for his glory) againſt our ſelues, when theſe firſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions be well vnderſtood, and applyed of vs, we shalbe able (by his grace) to frame more comforta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble premiſſes, and to goe forward in this <hi>divine diſcep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation,</hi>
                  <pb n="82" facs="tcp:20806:46"/> with conſideration of thoſe further things, the concluſion and inference wherof, will miniſter vnto vs yet <hi>more courage,</hi> to cleave vnto the Lord in the communion of his ſaints.</p>
               <p>For why? the <hi>former argument</hi> was taken from the <hi>miſeryes, greivances, perſecutions,</hi> and <hi>oppreſſions</hi> of Gods people, and yet it is powerfull, and able to conclude, both a <hi>neceſſity,</hi> (and includeth alſo an <hi>excellency</hi>) of our ſeparation from ſinners, to become of that number who are ſoe happy, in their very <hi>miſery:</hi> but <hi>this latter</hi> may be taken from the <hi>graces</hi> of the ſame men from whoſe diſtreſſes alone, we reaſoned before; and for the <hi>further wooing,</hi> and <hi>faster glewing</hi> of vs vnto the heavenly corporation, of ſuch as are happily incor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porated into <hi>Chrict Ieſus,</hi> it may (in the ſecond place) be framed thus.</p>
               <p>If the <hi>worſt</hi> of Gods people viz: their troubles, mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeryes, and oppreſſions, be ſuch as doe exceede all the wellbeing of other men, if in their <hi>greivances</hi> and vexations, it goe ſoe well with them, how happy muſt theſe men be conſidered in their <hi>graces,</hi> and the em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment of them? if their bitter ſorrowes be ſoe <hi>ſweete,</hi> how will the <hi>ſweete ſap,</hi> and ſavour of God ſpirit taſte, and relish in them? if out of cruelty, tyranny, and all manner of evill ſoe much good may iſſue, when they haue to doe with wicked and vnreaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble men, who can conceive the conſolation that shall accrew vnto them, in the free and peaceable excer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe of their graces, wherein they deale only with Gods owne majeſty, and ſuch of their fellow brethe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren and ſiſters, as are truly gracious with themſelues? if the troubled waters, which are ſoe muddyed with the foule fruit of <hi>Satans,</hi> and mens mallice, may yeelde
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:20806:46"/> ſuch joy, what will flow from the bleſſed jnfluence of God himſelf thinke yee, when he shall leade them to thoſe wells of ſalvation, whence they shall <hi>draw freely,</hi> and <hi>drinke their fill,</hi> of thoſe pure chriſtall ſtreames, which himſelf hath diſtilled? Surely every man muſt needes (in all reaſon) thinke, that if their <hi>worſt estate</hi> of greife and miſery be <hi>ſo good,</hi> this of grace and peace, cannot but be <hi>better,</hi> and yeelde ſweeter fruit then the former; and ſoe the <hi>beſt eſtate</hi> of a wicked man, being ſo farre behinde their <hi>worſt,</hi> muſt needes be much more behinde this, and vtterly incomparable there-vnto.</p>
               <p>And yet, though this be <hi>much,</hi> the <hi>moſt,</hi> and <hi>beſt</hi> of all, is yet to come, viz: their ſtate of <hi>glory,</hi> which shal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be the reward both of their <hi>greivances,</hi> and <hi>graces</hi> alſo; &amp; from that, a man whoſe hart were ſet aright, might <hi>laſtly</hi> reaſon thus.</p>
               <p>Theſe men <hi>(Gods ſaints)</hi> were happier then I, at the <hi>worſt</hi> of their miſeryes, even in the midſt of their ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myes; They were yet more happy then ſoe, when with their <hi>God,</hi> and with each other among themſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues, they might peaceably vſe their <hi>graces;</hi> the leaſt of theſe two, was more then a litle beyond my beſt: But their <hi>best</hi> of all, being yet to come, <hi>to wit,</hi> their bleſſednes and glory in heaven, with the <hi>God</hi> of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven; what shall I conceive of their inconceivable fae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licity, then and there? and how infinitely vnhappy are <hi>I,</hi> that am ſoe short of the <hi>good</hi> they haue, in their <hi>very evill?</hi> and am not yet come ſo farre, as to be e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quall with them in their meaneſt, and moſt afflicted condition? Surely it being ſo well with them in their <hi>greivances;</hi> it cannot but be much better with them in their <hi>graces,</hi> and <hi>beſt of all</hi> in their <hi>glory.</hi> O the hydden,
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:20806:47"/> 
                  <hi>(yet heavenly)</hi> eſtate of theſe holy ones; which is ſoe heavenly, that it muſt be <hi>hydden,</hi> there being no poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibility on earth to reveale it. <hi>Who</hi> would be out of that ſtate, wherein is ſoe much excellency, that every <hi>evill</hi> therein, is exceeding <hi>good,</hi> and every <hi>good</hi> excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth each other? If a mans hart be not <hi>chayned</hi> to the <hi>Divell,</hi> &amp; by the <hi>Divell,</hi> to the <hi>world,</hi> to be kept here, in that perpetuall <hi>priſon</hi> of infidelity, and profanes, which will bring him to that <hi>perditio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  </hi> which is due there vnto; he cannot but be drawne out of himſelf, and his ſinfull ſtate, with this <hi>threefolde corde,</hi> and be tyed faſt for ever (as one enamoured and enflamed) to the <hi>Lord God,</hi> in the felowship of thoſe <hi>his ſaints,</hi> who ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving beene faithfull before him here, (both in <hi>doing</hi> his will, and <hi>ſuffering</hi> for the ſame) haue now received the wages, both of their <hi>faith,</hi> and <hi>ſufferings,</hi> in the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome for which they ſuffered, wherein they shall ſee <hi>him as he is,</hi>
                  <note place="margin"> 1 Ioh. 3.2</note> and with <hi>him,</hi> his bleſſed <hi>Son,</hi> his eternall <hi>Spirit,</hi> his beloved <hi>Saints,</hi> in that life and jmmortality, bliſſe, and faelicity, which <hi>God</hi> who is faithfull, hath <hi>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed to them, promiſed to vs,</hi> and to all the reſt of his holy ones,
<note place="margin"> Heb. 11.40.</note> keeping them, who are <hi>already</hi> in actuall po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, not abſolutely perfect <hi>(as being yet without vs)</hi> till <hi>we</hi> shalbe brought vnto <hi>them,</hi> &amp; both <hi>they,</hi> and <hi>we,</hi> (and all the elect) vnto the Lord our God, at the laſt day, to be compleate in that entyre, and eternall per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of glory, the <hi>hope</hi> wherof, giue's vs hart, and make's vs wayte, and ſigh in our ſoules, looking and longing for that glorious appearance of his, which shall make vs to appeare in glory with him, for ever and ever.</p>
               <closer>AMEN.</closer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
